<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sacred eloquence: or, the art of rhetorick, as it is layd down in Scripture. By the right Reverend Father John Prideaux late Lord Bishop of VVorcester.</title>
            <author>Prideaux, John, 1578-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1790_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209683</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170374</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170374)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 223:E1790[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sacred eloquence: or, the art of rhetorick, as it is layd down in Scripture. By the right Reverend Father John Prideaux late Lord Bishop of VVorcester.</title>
                  <author>Prideaux, John, 1578-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson, for George Sawbridge, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Bible on Ludgate-Hill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rhetoric --  1500-1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170374:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SACRED ELOQUENCE: Or, the Art of RHETORICK, As it is layd down in Scripture.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father <hi>JOHN PRIDEAVX</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>VVORCESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> —</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Wilſon,</hi> for <hi>George Sawbridge,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the <hi>Bible</hi> on <hi>Ludgate-Hill,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170374:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170374:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SACRED</hi> ELOQUENCE: OR, The Art of Rhetorick, as it is laid down in Scripture.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ACRED ELO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUENCE</hi> is a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall kind of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, to be uſed in Prayer, Preaching, or Conference; to the glory of God, and the convincing, inſtructing, and ſtrengthning our brethren.</p>
               <p>The meditation of which gave <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid more understanding than all his tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170374:3"/>Pſal.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.19.</note> 119.19. proved a <hi>Hammer</hi> to <hi>Jeremy, that breaketh the rocks in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<note place="margin">Jer. 23.29.</note> chap.</hi> 23.29. was St. <hi>Pauls Engine, for the pulling down of ſtrong holds, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th it ſelf againſt the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</note> 5.</p>
               <p>At which, uſed by our Saviour, the people were aſtoniſhed; <hi>For he taught them as one having authority,
<note place="margin">Matth 7.28.</note> and not as the Scribes, Matth.</hi> 7.28. His perverſe Country-men of <hi>Nazareth</hi> bare him witneſſe, and <hi>wondred at the gratious words that proceeded out of his mouth,
<note place="margin">Luk. 4.22.</note> Luk.</hi> 4.22. And the fee'd Officers, ſent to apprehend him, returned with this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, <hi>Never man ſpake like this man, Joh.</hi> 7.46.
<note place="margin">Joh. 7.46.</note> For it <hi>pricketh in the hearts of the hearers,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>The word of God is quick and powerfull, and ſharper then any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding aſſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, Heb.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> 4, 12.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170374:3"/>
               <p>In this eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially may be obſerved,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Tropes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Figures.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Schemes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Patheticks.</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Darbenoth, ſtimuli</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>quibus boves punguniur: &amp; Maſmeroth, clavi qui retinent illud, cui infiguntur.</hi> Eccl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> . 12.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, Act. 2.37.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Characters.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Antiſheſes.</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim 6.20. <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits.</hi> Gal. 5.17</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Parallels.</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Alluſions, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, cor-eſpondencies.</note>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>vertere,</hi> To turn; A flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of ſpeech, whereby a word is turned or changed from his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation into another. <hi>Cicero, de c'ar. Orat.</hi> calleth them, <hi>Verborum immutationes;</hi> in his Partitions, <hi>Verba modificata.</hi> It differeth from a Figure or Scheme, becauſe the one doth alter the habit of or make a change in, the Words onely; the other, in the Speech. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>utar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> in vit Homer. Dictionum vero immutatio, appellatur Trepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> compoſitionis contrà, Schema.</hi> Both the ſpecies of Elocution.</note> Tropes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TRopes</hi> carry with them, in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the phraſeologie of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Tongues, far differing in weight and majeſty from Ethnick Aſhdodiſm.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170374:4"/>
                  <p>Moſt uſefull amongſt theſe may be noted,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <note n="1" place="margin">
                              <hi>Hyperbole</hi> and <hi>Catachreſis</hi> are by ſome modern Rhetoritians ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted affections of a <hi>Trope,</hi> rather than <hi>Tropes</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; becauſe there is no <hi>Trope,</hi> but may be ſet forth in too harſh and unequall a dreſſe, which is a <hi>Catachreſis;</hi> or be ſcrewed up too high in hyperbolicall expreſſions. Yet neither <hi>Tully, Quintilian,</hi> nor any of the Antients obſerve this exactneſſe, but number them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Tropes,</hi> as doth the Author.</note>
1. <hi>Hyperbole.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <note n="2" place="margin">
                              <hi>Hyperbole</hi> and <hi>Catachreſis</hi> are by ſome modern Rhetoritians ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted affections of a <hi>Trope,</hi> rather than <hi>Tropes</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; becauſe there is no <hi>Trope,</hi> but may be ſet forth in too harſh and unequall a dreſſe, which is a <hi>Catachreſis;</hi> or be ſcrewed up too high in hyperbolicall expreſſions. Yet neither <hi>Tully, Quintilian,</hi> nor any of the Antients obſerve this exactneſſe, but number them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Tropes,</hi> as doth the Author.</note>
2. <hi>Catachreſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <note n="3" place="margin">
                              <hi>Emphaſis</hi> is rather a <hi>Figure</hi> than <hi>Trope,</hi> in preciſneſſe of ſpeech; it belongeth not to the ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a word, but ſentence, which, by this <hi>Figure,</hi> is ſo pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, or otherwiſe notified, that what lyeth hid, and muffled under a clowd, doth manifeſtly appear. <hi>Emphaſis eſt etiam inter figuras, cum ex aliquo dicto latens aliquid eruitur.</hi> But the Author taketh a <hi>Trope</hi> in the ſame latitude <hi>Quintilian doth, l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>(Tropus eſt ſermo à natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali &amp; principali fignificatione ad aliam, ornandae oracionis gratiâ)</hi> and ſo <hi>Emphaſis</hi> may be permitted to ſtand where it doth.</note>
3. <hi>Emphaſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Metonymia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Ironia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. <hi>Metaphora.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. <hi>Synecdoche.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Excedere, ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare;</hi> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of truth, either by ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating it too high, or depreſſing it, as low. <hi>Superlatio, ac trajectio veritatis, minuendi augendive cauſâ, Cicer. de Orat. l.</hi> 3. So all am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifications and extenuations, beyond or below their juſt meaſure, may be termed Hyperbolicall; although the words whereby they are expreſſed be not borrowed, but proper. Whence that of <hi>Virgil, Eclog.</hi> 9. <hi>Candidior cygnis, hederâ formoſior albâ.</hi> that of <hi>Plaut. in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lular. Pumex non aequè est aridus, atque hic ſenex,</hi> and ſuch like, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Rhetoritians to be hyperbolicall expreſſions, though the words remain unaltered from their native habit and ſignification. This <hi>Beumler</hi> will not endure, and therefore hath excogitated a double Hyperbole, the one Logicall, the other Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: the Logicall, where, in proper words the thing is hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolically ſet forth; Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall, where there are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper or borrowed tearms uſed, for the amplyfying or extenuating a thing.</note> Hyperbole.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hyperbolicall</hi> ſpeeches are theſe, or the like, in the old Teſtament: <hi>Judah
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170374:4"/>ſhall bind his fole unto the vine, and his aſſes-colt unto the choiſe vine, and waſh his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in wine, and his cloths in the blood of the grape, Gen.</hi> 49.11. expreſſing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary plenty of wine that ſhall ſtream in his coaſt. So <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.17. <hi>A land flowing with milk and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. The rivers, the floods, the brooks of hony and butter, Job.</hi> 20.17. hyperbolically ſpeak an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible abundance. <hi>With hony out of the rock ſhould I have ſatisfied thee, Pſal.</hi> 81.16. <hi>i.e.</hi> By means which could not be expected. In like manner the fierceneſſe of the Horſe is ſet forth, by <hi>ſwallowing the ground with his rage, and ſaying, Ha, ha, amongſt the trumpets, Job</hi> 39.24, 25. The vaſtneſſe of the <hi>Behemoth,</hi> by <hi>drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up a river, and truſting that he can draw up Jordan into his mouth, Job</hi> 40.23. The hideouſneſſe of the <hi>Leviathan, whoſe eyes are like the eye-lids of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, out of whoſe mouth go burning lamps, whoſe breath kindleth coals; that maketh the deep to boyle like a pot, and the ſea like a pot of oyntment; by reaſon of whoſe plunging, the mighty through fear
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170374:5"/>(purgant alvum,</hi> ſaith one) <hi>purifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> (ſo our Tranſlation) <hi>Job</hi> 41.25. which ſet forth an unutterable terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, not to be reached in other Languages. So, <hi>the skipping of mountains like Rams, and of little Hills like Lambs. Pſal.</hi> 114. would have us to conceive the ſhattering of the fineſt creatures at the Creator's preſence. In the New Teſtament, <hi>The paſſing of a Camell thorough the eye of a needle, Mat.</hi> 9.24. <hi>The Stars falling to the earth, as a figg tree ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth her untimely figgs: the departing of the heaven as a ſcrowl rowled together, Revel.</hi> 6.13.14. <hi>The whole world cannot containe the books,</hi> wherein our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's acts ſhould be written, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.25. may not litterally be taken, but as ſublime Hyperboles, expreſſing in the firſt, a matter of the greateſt difficulty; in the ſecond, a foretelling of ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious confuſion; in the laſt, the not regiſtred acts of our Saviour, hardly, and not neceſſary to be recounted of. So ſin is confeſſed in tearms to be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolically ſinfull, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Light affliction,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in an eminent hyperbolicall manner, <hi>to work an eternall weight of glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledgeth, that,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170374:5"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, before his converſion, <hi>he perſecuted the Church, Gal.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Abuſio,</hi> ſo called, when for want of a fit name to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe a thing by, we borrow that word which commeth neareſt to hand; by which means it commeth to paſſe, that the word is abuſed, and the Trope is more harſh and unequall: as,
<q>—<hi>equum divina Palladis arte Aedificant</hi>—</q>
                     </note> Catachreſis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Catachreſis,</hi> abuſed (as it were) or far-fetched incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous ſpeeches, may be tearmed ſuch, as, <hi>All the earth was of one lip, and one ſort of words, Gen.</hi> 11.1. that is, of one Language, and ſpake one Tongue. <hi>Let us ſmite him with the tongue, Jer.</hi> 18.18.
<note place="margin">Jer. 18.18.</note> that is, Slander him. <hi>I will open the ſhoulder of Moab from his Cities, Ezech.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 25.9.</note> 25.9. that is, Diſmantle his Townes to make way for his enemies. <hi>I will turn to the people a pure lip, that they may call upon the name of the Lord, to ſerve him with one ſhoulder, Zeph.</hi> 3.9.
<note place="margin">Zeph 3.9.</note> that is, with one conſent. So, <hi>Daubing with untempered morter,</hi> and <hi>ſowing pillowes under arm-holes, Ezech.</hi> 13.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.</note> are unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to expreſſe deceitfull and flattering doctrine; much more that (as the <hi>Doway</hi> Bible gives it) <hi>in the Canticle of my Coſen, concerning his vineyard in Horn; the ſon of oyle, Iſai.</hi> 5.1. for,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.1.</note> Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated in a fertile or fruitfull hill.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170374:6"/>Likewiſe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
                     <hi>My ſoul is alway in my hand, Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>i. e.</hi> I am in eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>The ploughers plowed upon my back, and made long furrowes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 129. Joh. 8.5.</note> Pſal.</hi> 129. grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſly afflicted me. <hi>To ſee death, Joh.</hi> 8.51. for, To die. <hi>To ſhake off the duſt of the feet,
<note place="margin">Matth. 10.14.</note> Matth.</hi> 10.14. for, Utterly to renounce or abandon. <hi>To pluck out the eye and caſt it from us,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.29.</note> Matth.</hi> 5.29. to take away occaſions; are elegancies in Scripture, which otherwiſe might ſeem catachreſticall. So merit, and wages, or reward are urged, which import no more then a good work; and wages is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe it is paid in the evening, when the work is done. Alſo plenty of all things is expreſſed by 1. <hi>Butter of Kine;</hi> and 2. <hi>Milk of Sheep;</hi> and 3. <hi>Fat of Rams;</hi> and 4. <hi>Rams of the breed of Baſhan;</hi> and 5 <hi>Goats,</hi> with 6. <hi>the fat of the kidneys of Wheat;</hi> and 7. <hi>the pure blood of the Grape for drink,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.14.</note> Deuter.</hi> 32.14. So, I might have received mine own <hi>with uſury;</hi> that is, with increaſe, a Catachreſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Synecdoche, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.27. From one dead, ſprang ſo many as the ſtars of heaven,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.12. Heb. 12.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and as the ſand beſide <hi>the lip of the ſea</hi> innumerable, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.12. <hi>A clowd of witneſſes, Heb.</hi> 12.1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170374:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>ſpeciem praebere, repraeſentare;</hi> becauſe thereby is a repreſentation made of ſome ſpeciall thing that lyeth hid in the words; which is made manifeſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the pronountlation of them, or by the affixing of ſome demonſtrative article to them; and this, when it is not ſo ſafe or meet to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our ſenſe in words at length. <hi>Virgil. Non licuit tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lami expertem ſine crimine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, Degere, more ferae! Virum te praestes oportet.</hi>
                     </note> Emphaſis.</head>
                  <p>As <hi>Catachreſticalls</hi> make an impreſſion through their harſhneſſe and ſtrangeneſſe; ſo an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> worketh through its vigour, which in reading is enlivened by the pronunciation. Hitherto are referred ſuch epithets, wherein the Apoſtles are called the <hi>ſalt of the earth, Math.</hi> 5. wicked men, the <hi>men of Gods hand, Pſal.</hi> 17.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> employed ſometimes to chaſtiſe the godly. So, <hi>Man of ſorrowes, Iſa.</hi> 53.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.</note> 
                     <hi>Son of perdition, of Belial, of thunder, of the morning,</hi> have eſpeciall emphaſes in them. As alſo, <hi>Firſt born of death, king of terrours, bars of the pit, Job.</hi> 18.13, 14.
<note place="margin">Job 18.13. <hi>Ib.</hi> 17.16. <hi>Ib.</hi> 38.37.</note> 
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> 17.16. <hi>Bottles of heaven, Ib.</hi> 38.37. With which may be ranged thoſe high phraſes and ſtrains, <hi>Behold, I am againſt thee, O thou deſtroying mountain, (ſaith the Lord) which deſtroyeſt all the earth; and I will ſtretch out my hand upon thee, and roll thee down from the rocks, and I will make thee a burnt mountain, Jer.</hi> 51.25.
<note place="margin">Jer. 51.25.</note> 
                     <hi>I will make it a poſſeſſion for the Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170374:7"/>and pools of water, and I will ſweep it with the beeſome of deſtruction,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 14.23.</note> Iſa.</hi> 14.23. <hi>His breath ſhall ſift the Nations with the ſieve of vanity,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ib.</hi> 30.28.</note> Ibid</hi> 30.28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nominis pro nomine poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio:</hi> A putting of one word for another. By this Trope, the inventor is put for the thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, the poſſeſſor for the thing poſſeſſed, the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for the thing contained, and the efficient for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp;c. By <hi>Cicero</hi> tearmed <hi>Hypallage, immutatio &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductio, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Orat. Traductio &amp; immutatio in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o.</hi>
                     </note> Metonymia.</head>
                  <p>Amongſt <hi>Metonymies,</hi> thoſe wherein the cauſe and the effect, the ſubject and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct, the antecedent and the conſequent, are taken one for another, are moſt of note and uſe. And the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Cain,</hi> Why art thou wroth, and why is thy countenance fallen? If thou doſt well, ſhalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doſt not well, <hi>ſin lyeth at the dore, Gen.</hi> 4.6, 7. [Sin] that is, the puniſhment for ſin, the cauſe for the effect; or, as ſome, [Sin] that is, the ſacrifice for ſin, a repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant heart in thy power; and therefore haſt no reaſon to lowre at my dealing with thee. For the ſecond, what more frequent in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then Sacramentall metonymies? as, To kill the paſſeover, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Kill the paſſeover.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18. <hi>Keep
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170374:7"/>or celebrate the feaſt of the paſſeover.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.1. <hi>Chriſt our paſſeover is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed for us, therefore let us keep the feaſt not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedneſſe, but with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened bread of ſincerity and truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. where, Paſſeover, the thing ſignified, is put for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorative and ſacrifice, by which it was to be preſented, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.14.27. In which metonymicall ſenſe, the words of inſtitution of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per muſt be underſtood, <hi>Hec eſt corpus meum, Matth.</hi> 20.26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. the Signe dignified with the name of the thing ſignified, for the aſſurance of the performance on the part of him who ſealed the evidence; except we would make a prodigie of the bleſſed Supper, appointed to ſet at variance, not in unity to fix believers. For the exemplification of the third kind of Metonymies, upon the mutuall change of antecedent and conſequent, with the thing to be expreſſed. So, <hi>To know a woman, to go in unto her, to be with her.</hi> Hath Ammon thy brother <hi>been with thee?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.20. ſerve modeſtly to expreſſe what may be done, without otherwiſe ſpeaking of it. So, <hi>Joſeph is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170374:8"/>not, and Simeon is not, Gen.</hi> 42.36. <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, becauſe they were not, Jer.</hi> 31.15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.18. by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſpeak their precedent death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Simulatio,</hi> Becauſe we ſpeak one thing, and mean another. <hi>Cum aliud in pectore recluſum, aliud in lingua habemus,</hi> as in the Poet. <hi>Scili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet is ſuperis labor est</hi>— It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called by <hi>Tully, Inverſio,</hi> a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upſide down of a thing, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the right form. A proper tearm to expreſſe this Trope where the contrary is meant to what is ſaid <hi>Euge bone ſerve! curâſti probè.</hi> There are ſix ſpecies of it, 1. <hi>Chleuaſmus,</hi> or <hi>Epicertomeſis.</hi> 2. <hi>Charientiſmus,</hi> or <hi>Scom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> 3. <hi>Aſtiſmus.</hi> 4 <hi>Diaſyrmus.</hi> 5. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uteniſmus.</hi> 6. <hi>Sarcaſmus.</hi>
                     </note> Ironia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ironies</hi> alſo find an admittance in both Teſtaments; for, <hi>He that dwelleth in heaven laugheth his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to ſcorn, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion. Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias mocked them</hi> [Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites] <hi>and ſaid, Cry aloud, for he is a god, either he is tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or purſuing, or he is in a journey, or peradventure he ſleepeth and muſt be awaked.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.27. So that ſpeech of <hi>Micajah</hi> to <hi>Ahab, Go up and proſper, for the Lord ſhall deliver it into the hands of the King,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22. can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with a true Prophets inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, if it be not paſſed with an Irony, as the King alſo took it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. By the like proverb (which is the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe) the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170374:8"/>
                     <hi>Lucifer, ſon of the morning, which did weaken the Nations, Iſa.</hi> 14.12. The Prince of <hi>Tyrus</hi> is alſo taunted, <hi>Behold, thou art wiſer then Daniel, there is no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret that they can hide from thee. VVith thy wiſdom and with thy understanding thou haſt gotten thee riches, and haſt gotten gold and ſilver into thy treaſures. By thy great wiſdom and by thy traffick haſt thou encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy riches, and thy heart is lifted up becauſe of thy riches, Ezek.</hi> 28.3, 4, 5. In the New Teſtament, that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour muſt needs be taken for an Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Full well ye reject the commandment of God, that ye may keep your own tradition. Fill ye up then the meaſure of your fathers, Matth.</hi> 23.32. And that, <hi>Sleep on now, and take your reſt; behold, the hour is at hand, and the ſon of man is betrayed into the hands of ſinners, Matth.</hi> 26.45. So that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as Kings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us; I would to God ye did reigne, that we alſo might reigne with you,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. More bitter and baſer were thoſe Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms of the ſouldiers to our Saviour, whom they had crowned with thorns, <hi>Hail King of the Jewes, Matth.</hi> 27.29. Milder that of the Apoſtles, <hi>Ye ſuffer fools gladly, ſeeing ye your ſelves are wiſe,</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170374:9"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. <hi>And what is it wherein ye were inferiour to other Churches, except it be that I my ſelf was not burthenſome unto you? forgive me this wrong, ib.</hi> 12.13. Some would have that to be ironically ſpoken, <hi>Rather give alms of ſuch things as ye have, and behold all things are clean unto you, Luk.</hi> 11.4. which others with greater reaſon deny.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tranſlatio,</hi> when a word is transferred from one thing unto another, by reaſon of the likeneſſe that is betwixt them. <hi>Nihil eſt in rerum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, cujus non in alijs rebus poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus uti vocabulo &amp; nomine. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de enim Simile, duci non potest? poteſt autem ex omnibus. Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem verbum unum quod ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem continet, tranſlatum lumen affert orationi.</hi> The Greek Rhetoricians under this notion did comprehend all the Tropes. <hi>Ariſt.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Id Rhetor. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. So <hi>Cicero ad Brutum.</hi> Though the variety of this Trope be very great, and field large; yet <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> endeavours to reduce it into four ranks. 1 When one ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate is put for another, as <hi>Cato</hi> barked at <hi>Scipio.</hi> 2 Inanimate for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other as —<hi>Claſſique immit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>it habenas.</hi> 3 Inanimates for animates, as <hi>ferro an fato virtus Argivûm occidit?</hi> 4 Animates for inanimates, as, <hi>—Sedet inſcius (metus) alto.</hi>
                     </note> Metaphora.</head>
                  <p>As Metonymies, ſo <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors</hi> in Scripture are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and numberleſs. What haſt thou done? the <hi>voyce of thy brothers bloud cryeth unto me from the ground, Gen.</hi> 4.10. as an importunate Suiter crying for juſtice. We are come to Jeſus the Mediator of the New Teaſtament, and to the blood of ſprinkling, that <hi>ſpeaketh better things, then that of</hi> Abel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170374:9"/>whoſe alſo, being dead, yet <hi>ſpeaketh, Heb.</hi> 11.4. Speech is here tranſlated from man to blood. (2) We have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, mothers, brothers, ſiſters, maſters, ſervants, and ſuch other relatives with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtint, metaphorically taken. So God is ſaid to be father of all. Hath the rayne <hi>a father? or who hath begatten the drops of dew? Job</hi> 38.28. none but God, that created them. The child (Chriſt) is called the everlaſting <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Iſa.</hi> 9.6. The divell is a liar, and the <hi>father of it, Joh.</hi> 8.44. that is, the author, inventor, propagator. <hi>Jabal,</hi> and <hi>Jubal,</hi> the <hi>fathers of ſuch as dwell in Tents,</hi> keep cattle, handle the harp or Organ, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.20.21. <hi>Micah's</hi> maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt muſt be a <hi>father</hi> to the plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Danites, <hi>Judg.</hi> 18.19. that is, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor. One <hi>Joab</hi> is the <hi>father</hi> of the valley <hi>Charaſhim,</hi> for they were crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Eliſha</hi> cryeth after <hi>Elijah,</hi> My <hi>father,</hi> my <hi>father,</hi> the Chariot of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof, 1 <hi>King</hi> 2.12. a ſurer protector, then all their Martialiſts with their beſt forces. With the ſame, King <hi>Joaſh</hi> reverenceth <hi>Eliſha, ib.</hi> 13, 14. And <hi>Naamans</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants honour their Maſter, My <hi>Father,</hi> if the Prophet had bid thee do ſome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170374:10"/>great thing, wouldeſt thou not have done it? <hi>Ib.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Job</hi> ſtoopes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge corruption to be <hi>his Father,</hi> and the worme to be <hi>his Mother</hi> and <hi>Siſter</hi> in regard of his wofull plight, <hi>Job</hi> 17.14. And our Saviours poſition is catholick, Whoſoever ſhall do the will of God, the ſame is my <hi>Siſter, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Mother, Mar.</hi> 3.25. not by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration but acceptation. In an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſenſe is the inſcription on <hi>Babylons</hi> fore-head, Myſtery, <hi>Babylon</hi> the great, the <hi>Mother</hi> of harlots, and abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.5. In as far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetch'd Metaphors we have <hi>The ſons of the quiver,</hi> for arrows, <hi>Job</hi> 41.28. <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Jonah's</hi> goard ſhall be the <hi>Son of a night, Jon.</hi> 4.10. The paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call-Lamb a male, <hi>the Son of the firſt year, Exod.</hi> 12.9. Corn the <hi>Son of the threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floore, Iſa.</hi> 21.20. the <hi>Owles daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Ib.</hi> 3.21. that is, Chicken. Villages belonging to <hi>Bethſhean</hi> and other Cities are ſaid to be their daughters, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 17. Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem, Sion,</hi> or <hi>Babylon</hi> are the inhabitants which acknowledg thoſe places for Mothers. In which ſenſe, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>Mother of us all, Gal.</hi> 4.26. To this Trope are referred <hi>Anthropopathies,</hi> wherein
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170374:10"/>hands, and eyes, and eares, and other members, and humane affections are referred to God, and Spirits: which <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> taking literally were condemned for Hereticks. Of this kind are theſe paſſages, It <hi>repented</hi> the Lord that he had made man on the earth, <hi>and it grieved Him at the Heart, Gen.</hi> 6.6. <hi>His ſoul was grieved</hi> for the miſery of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, Judg.</hi> 10.16. Let me alone that <hi>my wrath</hi> may wax hot againſt them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.10. The Lord <hi>repented</hi> of the evill that he thought to do unto his people, <hi>v.</hi> 14. and the like. In which expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, for mans weak capacity, God is ſaid to do ſuch things out of paſſion, which from eternity he had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: as men do out of weakneſs, when they change their minds. No change being in God, but in the things done: which fall out in men according to the mutability of their purpoſes, carried on by paſſion, <hi>Thou tellest my wandrings, put my teares in thy bottle. Are they not in thy book? Pſal.</hi> 56.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Comprehenſio, intellectio. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectio est cum, res tota parva de parte cognoſcitur, aut de toto parva pars.</hi> Author <hi>ad Heren.</hi>
                     </note> Synecdoche.</head>
                  <p>Of <hi>Synecdoches,</hi> are met with no leſſe ſtore, 1. In
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170374:11"/>generalls put for particulars, Preach the word to <hi>every Creature, Mar.</hi> 16.15. meaning, that is capable of it. The ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt expectation of <hi>the creature</hi> waiteth for the manifeſtation of the ſons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. all ſorts of men hoping to have their ſtates bettered. Submit your ſelves to <hi>every humane Creature</hi> for the Lords ſake, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. that is, every man to whom you are ſubordinate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God will have it ſo, 2. Special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties put for generalls, as, The <hi>Sun</hi> ſhall not burn thee by day, nor the <hi>Moon</hi> by night, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1216. that is, nothing ſhall hurt thee. <hi>Edom, and Moab, and Ammon</hi> have confederated or covenanted to take unto themſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>i.e.</hi> the progeny of ſuch wicked perſons. So ſouls are put for perſons, <hi>All the ſouls</hi> that came into <hi>Egypt</hi> with <hi>Jacob</hi> were 70. that is all the perſons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.27. His travell ſhall fall upon his own <hi>head,</hi> and his wickedneſſe upon his owne pate, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 7.16. his perſon ſhall endure the brunt of it. Is not the <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Joab</hi> in all this? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Joabs</hi> advice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. 3. A ſynecdoche is frequently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in putting a ſet number for an indefinite, and reciprocally. If we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170374:11"/>would contend with God we cannot anſwer <hi>one for a Thouſand,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.8. that is, a great multitude: by which trope, 7 is often put for many, or an unlimited number. The women ſaid to <hi>Naomi</hi> concerning <hi>Obed,</hi> He ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee a reſtorer of life, and a nouriſher of thine old age. For thy daughter in law which loveth thee; which is better to thee then 7 <hi>Sons,</hi> hath born him, <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.15. So an evil ſpirit caſt out, when he returns, is ſaid to take with him 7 other ſpirits, which makes the re-poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of him that was freed worſe, than when he was firſt poſſeſſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.45.</p>
                  <p>It is a good caution put in by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſtinus de Doctr. Chriſtia. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.</note> that <hi>To urge a trope according to the letter, and that which is literally taken to wreſt to a trope, in ſome ſort verifieth that of the Apoſtle, The letter killeth, but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit giveth life,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. Such a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Diſciples were guilty of, who underſtood the <hi>leaven of the Phariſees,</hi> and Sadduces, which their Maſter war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them to take heed of, to be lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally meant of bread, which ſhould have been underſtood metaphorically of their leaven of doctrine, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.12. And the falſe witneſſes alledged
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170374:12"/>againſt Chriſt the deſtroying of the materiall Temple, which was ſpoken of him by a Trope concerning the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Body, <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.21. Theſe tropes twiſted together in a ſpeech continuate are as ſparkling Diamonds in a Ring, by the Apoſtle termed an allegory,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Gal. 4.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24.</p>
                  <p>And may be conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly diſcerned in
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Types.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Myſteries.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Apologues.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Parables.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Apothegms.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. <hi>Reproofs.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>exemplar, figura,</hi> a picture, or ſhadow of things to come, <hi>qui in veteri teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento praefiguravit aliquid in novo: fit tribus modis vel.</hi> 1. <hi>Natura: vel.</hi> 2. <hi>Hominum confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio: vel.</hi> 3. <hi>Dei.</hi>
                     </note> Types.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> by the Apoſtle are urged as types of difference between the old and new Teſtament; as anſwerable to <hi>Sinai</hi> in bondage, and free <hi>Jeruſalem, Gal.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Iſraels</hi> reducing from <hi>Egypt,</hi> mentioned by the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11.1. is made a type by the evangeliſt of our Saviours returning from thence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.15. The deliverance by the arke ſaid to be a type of baptiſme, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170374:12"/>as likewiſe the lifting up of the braſen Serpent a type of Chriſt's lifting up on the Croſſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 14. The paſſing of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> thorough the red ſea, mannah, the cloud, and the rock; ſet down as types of the Sacraments of the New Teſtament, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. So, to take ſuch precepts literally, as, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſeethe a kid in his mothers milk, Exod.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not plough with an aſſe and an ox together, Deut.</hi> 22.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the corn, Ib.</hi> 25.4. and not morally, for avoiding cruelty, parting ſtakes in worſhipping, and defrauding the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of his due, the Apoſtle brandeth as groſſe; for, (ſaith he) <hi>Doth God take care for oxen?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d.</hi> An hidden ſecret in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the knowledge of which is not attainable by any ſtrength of fleſh and blood, but by divine revelation.</note> Myſteries.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mysteries,</hi> under aenig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes or hidden ſpeeches, contain matter either 1. <hi>Morall:</hi> 2. <hi>Sacramentall:</hi> 3. <hi>Propheticall;</hi> for informing of manners, by way of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; confirming of promiſes, or points of belief; or fore-warning of things to come, for the good of Gods
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170374:13"/>people, and terrour of their oppoſites. For inſtances in either: <hi>Without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie great is the myſtery of godlineſſe. God was manifeſt in the fleſh, juſtified in the ſpirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the world, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>To you it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of God, but to them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, all things are done in parables, Mar.</hi> 4.11. Of theſe myſteries, the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors are the diſpenſers: <hi>Let a man ſo account of us as of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and ſtewards of the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Which mystery was kept ſecret ſince the world began, but now is made manifeſt by the ſcriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the everlaſting God, made known to all nations for the obedience of faith, Rom.</hi> 16.25, 26. This is called, <hi>The wiſdom of God in a myſtery, not revealed to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this world,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. Which is uttered by the Apoſtle, <hi>not in words which mans wiſdom teacheth, but which the holy Ghoſt teacheth, comparing ſpirituall things with ſpirituall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Doctrinall myſteries</hi> are ſeconded by <hi>Sacramentall,</hi> as the myſtery of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and regeneration by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170374:13"/>and the Lords Supper. Chriſts ſpirituall marriage with his Church, (ſo gloriouſly ſet out by <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 45. and <hi>Solomon,</hi> thorough the whole book of <hi>Canticles</hi>) is tearmed a great myſtery, ſomewhat opened by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire love that ſhould be between man and wife, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.32.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. All Prophecies, not underſtood or fulfilled, remain as myſteries; ſo are ſtyled the ſeven Stars and golden Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. Concerning the calling of the Jewes, to be expected in latter times: <hi>I would not, brethren, that ye ſhould be ignorant</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>of this myſtery, leſt ye ſhould be wiſe in your own conceits, that blindneſſe in part is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Iſrael untill the fulneſſe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils come in, and ſo all Iſrael ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, Rom.</hi> 11.25. He, that no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands under unknown tongues, or Tropes, may ſpeak myſteries: <hi>I will tell thee the myſtery of the woman</hi> (ſaith the Angel) <hi>and the beaſt that carrieth her, which hath the ſeven heads and ten horns, Rev.</hi> 17. And ſo the ſame Angel muſt tell us of the number of the beaſt, though it be the number of a man, and ſet down to be 666. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.18. And the 1000 years of the Saints reign up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170374:14"/>earth, whilſt Satan is chained in priſon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. Of the overthrow of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> in the Battle of <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon,</hi> and the like, before we ſhall decipher ſuch myſteries. So the Ark, Urim and Thummim; ſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s cup of the Lords fury, and dregs of the cup of trembling, <hi>cap.</hi> 51.17. <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>'s cup of conſolation for the death of father or mother, <hi>cap.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel's</hi> cup of aſtoniſhment and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>cap.</hi> 23.33. our Saviour's cup, which he prayed, conditionally, might paſſe from him, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.36. the cup the Apoſtles were to drink of, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.23. the devils cup, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. the golden cup of the great whore, full of abhominations, and filthineſſe of her fornications, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. are full of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Tropes, without the knowledge of which, they cannot be underſtood. As neither the myſticall books of <hi>Job</hi>'s logicall diſcourſes, <hi>David</hi>'s rhetoricall Pſalms, <hi>Solomon</hi>'s morall Inſtitutions, and Canticall Paſtoralls, can any way be opened without the ſame key, as <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Riddle, <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.12. the hand-writing againſt <hi>Belſhazzar, Dan.</hi> 5.25. our Saviour's, <hi>Whereſoever the carcaſe is, thither will the eagles reſort, Matth.</hi> 24.28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170374:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Apthon:</hi> A feigned ſpeech, under which the truth is repreſented, as in a picture. <hi>Aliud aperte dicit, aliud ex eo innuit ac profitetur; ergo,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>nonnulli appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare auſi ſunt <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, ſermones à ſermone, unum ab alio concluſum: Martinius:</hi> There are three kinds, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, Morall, and Mixt. Rationall, wherein ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is feigned to be done by man. Morall, which doth imitate the manners of thoſe things that are void of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as Brutes, Trees, &amp;c. Mixt, that doth conſiſt of both; all deſigned to inſtruct man, and inform his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> Apologues.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apologues</hi> are here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not ſuch as are to be rejected, as old wives, [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. Jewiſh, [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.] Sophiſticall, [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. but ſuch as are taken from irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall creatures, wherein one thing is ſaid, but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meant; in which kind is that <hi>of the Trees,</hi> where the <hi>baſe Bramble uſurps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall authority,</hi> which the Olive, Fig-tree, and Vine refuſed, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.7. That of the poor mans one little ewe lamb, which touched <hi>David</hi> to the quick, for his tyrannicall dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with honeſt <hi>Uriah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. That of <hi>Jehoaſh</hi> to <hi>Amaziah</hi> of the Thiſtle, which would match his ſon to the Cedar of <hi>Lebanon</hi>'s daughter, wherein he handſomly girdeth at his over-wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning preſumption, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 14.9. All which are a concatenation of divers Tropes, which from unreaſonable creatures teach men to be reaſonable:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170374:15"/>Which kind of teaching ſome have not unfitly called <hi>Zoopaedia.</hi> An <hi>Onoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paedia</hi> from Scripture-names might in like ſort be framed; as from <hi>Adam, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; Cain, poſſeſſion; Abel, vanity,</hi> may be congruouſly gathered, that all earthly poſſeſſion is vanity. From <hi>Miſhma, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah,</hi> and <hi>Maſſah,</hi> the names of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Iſhmael, Gen.</hi> 25.4; the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes gather by their Grammaticall derivation, that in deſtructive times, many things are to be heard, not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, but born with, when no other remedy may be hoped for. From <hi>Dib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laim</hi> the mother,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fagius</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Gomer</hi> the daughter; from <hi>Jezreel, Loruchamah,</hi> and <hi>Loammi</hi> the children, the corrupt condition of the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was repreſented to <hi>Hoſea.</hi> Whence may be inferred, that luxury and ſurquedry in a State, breeds a conſumption and overthrow, which begets diſperſion and deſolation, whereby the people become out of mercy, and not to be accounted any people at all, as the etymon of the words gives it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170374:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Suid. Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, collatio, quâ res diverſae o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stenduntur in aliquo eſſe ſimiles.</hi> Amongſt the Hebrews they were in ſo high eſteem, that any choiſe and rare ſentence they dignified with this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and thoſe things that were ſo, they covered with this veil, thereby not caſting their pearls before ſwine, to be trampled by them, and expoſed to contempt: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in imitated by the Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their Hieroglyphicks.</note> Parables.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Parables</hi> are differenced by ſome from Apologues, or fables, becauſe that they deſcend not to irrationall actors, as of brutes, or bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, but are bounded within the ſcene of ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall repreſentations. In which kind in the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, ſome make the whole Book of <hi>Job</hi> to be a pattern of a conference, grounded upon the true hiſtory of a man unexpectedly ruined, and miſtaken by his friends that came to viſit and comfort him. <hi>Solomon's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> to be a <hi>Sympoſium ſpirituale,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Wiſdom's invitation and chear is ſet out after an heavenly manner, where are Viands, 1. <hi>Ethicall.</hi> 2. <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,</hi> 3. <hi>Oeconomicall.</hi> 4. <hi>Aulicall.</hi> 5. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugall.</hi> 6. <hi>Experimentall.</hi> 7. <hi>Celeſtiall.</hi> The <hi>Canticles</hi> are acknowledged by all to be an <hi>Eclogue</hi> betwixt our Saviour and his Spouſe the Church, beyond imagination of Poets, and expreſſions of human affections. Of the ſame kind theſe pieces of <hi>Apocrypha, Tobit, Judith,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170374:16"/>Story of Suſanna, Bel and the Dragon,</hi> are by divers taken, which find more pith in the Morality, than ground for the Hiſtory. 2. In the New Teſtament, much of our Saviours Doctrine is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in parables, vvhereof ſeaven vve have in one Chapter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. In all, ſome have reckoned —. Amongſt vvhich, in the parable 1. <hi>of the ſower,</hi> is ſet forth the diverſe events of the ſame vvord preached, by reaſon of the divers diſpoſitions of the auditors: of vvhich, Some have eares to heare, ſome none: 2. In that of the <hi>prodigall Son</hi> returning to his forſaken Father,
<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> the cheerfull entertainment of a ſinner that unfeignedly repenteth: 3. In that of the <hi>freed debter</hi> by God,
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.20.</note> ſo tyrannical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impriſoning his brother, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy doome that befell him upon it; the neceſſity that vve ſhould forgive, if vve look to be forgiven: 4. In that of the <hi>labourers</hi> in the vineyard; and vvages pay'd them; that God endureth not Idlers, and rewards not as men exſpect, but of pleaſure, yet ſtill beyond exſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation: 5. The caſe of him that vvas for <hi>building of Barnes,</hi> inſtead of thankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to God that gave corne to fill them, <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.16. and of <hi>Dives and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170374:16"/>Lazarus;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> for vvordlings not to ſurfeit ſo here, that they ſuffer for it hereafter; and for the pious poor, left here to the dogs, to finde favour vvith the Angels: 6. In the paſſages parabolically ſet forth between <hi>the Prieſt, the Levite,
<note place="margin">Luk. 10.30.</note> the pittifull Samaritan, and the wounded Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller</hi> apparantly may be obſerved, that thoſe vvho are moſt obliged common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt neglect their duty; and help of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten commeth from vvhom, and vvhen, it might be leaſt exſpected: 7. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſpake this parable unto certaine vvhich <hi>truſted in themſelves, that they were righteous, and deſpiſed others,</hi> Luke. 18.9, 10. Tvvo men vvent up into the Temple to pray, the one a Phariſee, the other a Publican; their prayers and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures vve have, but the event ſhevvs, not the <hi>vaunting gifted man,</hi> that preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo high vvith his perfections; but the <hi>poor penitent,</hi> that ſtood a far off, not daring to lift up his eyes to Heaven, that ſmote his breaſt crying, GOD be mercifull to me a ſinner, came laſt, but ſped beſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170374:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Sententia brevis &amp; acuta, quae multa pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> Apothegms.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apothegms</hi> are ſpeeches of pregnant inſtruction, ſmart reproof, or profound conſequence; expreſſed in compendious propoſals, reſolvs, or replyes. As, when <hi>Benbadad ſends to Ahab,</hi> The Gods do ſo unto me, and more alſo, if the duſt of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſhall ſuffice for handfulls, for all the people that follow me. The King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> inferred, and ſaid, Tell him, <hi>Let not him that girdeth-on his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe boaſt himſelfe, as he that putteth it off,</hi> 1 King. 20.10, 11. for things may fall out unexpectedly, and events croſſe hopes and preſumptions. So of <hi>the wiſe Woman of Abel's propoſall</hi> to <hi>Joab,</hi> that furiouſly ſtormed the Citty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Summons given, they plainly ſpake in the beginning (it was noyſed firſt amongſt us of the Town, when we firſt admitted Sheba, and heard of thy purſuit) Surely, they will aske of <hi>Abell,</hi> and ſo make an end (they will not ſtrike before they ſpeak, or batter or throw down the walls, before they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand whether we are Royaliſts, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, that will juſtifie <hi>Sheba</hi>'s action) I am one of thoſe that am peaceable, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170374:17"/>faithfull in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou ſeekeſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a City, and a mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> why wilt thou ſwallow up the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Lord? a diſcreet and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et conference would take up the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This put <hi>Joab</hi> upon a ſight of his over-ſight, and an Epizeuxical acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, Far be it, far be it from me, that I ſhould ſwallow up, or deſtroy: 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.18, 19, 20. So, <hi>our Saviours anſwer to the combined Phariſees, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodians concerning tribute due to Caeſar,</hi> left them all to marvel, but not a word to reply, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.22. To <hi>Amaziahs meſſage,</hi> (a kind of challenge) Come and let us look one another in the face, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoaſh</hi>'s anſwer was pricking and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, The Sonne of The thiſtle was no fit match for the Cedar's daughter, 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 14.18. Our Saviour's Replies are here more then apothegmaticall: 1. To that of his mother, <hi>Son why hast thou dealt with us thus?
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.49.</note> Wist ye not that I must be about my Fathers buſineſſe:</hi> 2. To her motion, They have no Wine.
<note place="margin">Joh. 2.3, 4.</note> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? <hi>what have I to doe with thee? mine hour is not yet come:</hi> 3. To them that told him, <hi>that his Mother and his Brethren waited for him</hi> (whom by Nature he was bound to reſpect); <hi>he stretched forth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170374:18"/>his hands towards his Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.48.</note> and ſaid, Behold my Mother, and my Brethren: for, whoſoever ſhall doe the will of my Father which is in Heaven, the ſame is my Siſter, and Brother, and Mother</hi> (in my eſteem). <hi>My Mother and my Brethren are thoſe that hear the Word of God,
<note place="margin">Luk. 8.20.</note> and do it:</hi> 4. To that of the Phariſee, <hi>why do thy Diſciples tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the tradition of the Elders,
<note place="margin">Mar. 7.15.</note> in not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing their hands before meat?</hi> His ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction was, Not external ingredients, but internal, defile a man: 5. To that, <hi>Why eateth you Maſter with publicans and ſinners?
<note place="margin">Matth. 9.11.</note> Thoſe that be whole need not the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, but thoſe that are ſick. Go and learn what that meaneth, I will have Mercy, and not Sacrifice:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 2.18.</note> 6. To that, why his <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples faſted not as well as thoſe of John, and of the Phariſees?</hi> It was not ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable while the bridegroom was with them; and no more advantagious then to put a new patch upon an old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and new Wine into old veſſels, which will marre all, rather then make good: Things muſt be ſo ordered that they may doe good, and Diſciples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed that they may be edified: 7. To that,
<note place="margin">Mat. 2.27, 28.</note> 
                     <hi>Why do thy Diſciples pluck the eares of Corne upon the Sabbath day? which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</hi> They may do it, in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170374:18"/>as <hi>David</hi> are the ſhew-bread when he was hungry: And, <hi>the Sabbath was made for man, not man for the Sabbath. Therefore the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.</hi> Likewiſe him that intruded to be his follower, he diſcharged with,
<note place="margin">Luk. 9.58.</note> 
                     <hi>Foxes have holes, and the birds of the ayre have neſts, but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head.</hi> Thou wilt miſſe of thy ayme, if thou think to make a vvorldly fortune by follovving me. Him that put off his call,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/>
                     <hi>Let me firſt go and bury my Father,</hi> he leſſoneth, <hi>Let the dead bury the dead, but go thou and preach the Kingdome of God.</hi> So him that vvould comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vvith his friends, before he vvould ſerve his Maſter, he teacheth better manners,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/>
                     <hi>No man having put his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit for the Kingdome of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Reproofs, Complaints, and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations, mixed, or ſevered.</head>
                  <p>As in a building there muſt be a ſure foundation, ſtrong vvalls, and a good roof, othervviſe it vvill ſoon totter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.27. So in ſpiritual building, <hi>Scripture</hi> muſt be the ground-vvork, <hi>Liturgy</hi> the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170374:19"/>vvalls, and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> the roofe; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe it vvill never hold out againſt vvind and ſtormes. But <hi>Pharach</hi>'s dream is verified in us, The lean kine ſo devour the fat, that they leave no bones behind them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. And the famine of <hi>Samaria</hi> encreaſeth upon us, vvhere an aſſes head is prized at eighty pieces of ſilver; and the fourth part of a cab of dove's dung, for five: 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6. <hi>Gehazi</hi> vvill cheat both <hi>Naaman,</hi> and his Maſter, though the Leproſie attend it, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5. And <hi>Korah</hi> vvith his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices oppoſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> though the earth her ſelfe doth gape to ſvval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv them for it, and their families. Inſtead of acknovvledging of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, vve cry out vvith them in the prophet, <hi>we have no King becauſe we fear not the Lord,</hi> What ſhould a King do to us? <hi>falſe ſwearing, and a covenant will batter fit our plots,</hi> Hoſ. 10. We vvill not have this man ſhall reign over us, <hi>this is the heire come let us kill him, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance ſhall be ours,</hi> Matth. 21. Luke. 20. But ſhal the ſvvord devour for ever? vvill not this bring forth bitterneſſe in the end? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.26. In the mean vvhile <hi>Jonah,</hi> ſentt to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> flyes to <hi>Tarſhiſh;</hi> and vve, vvhen our Maſter is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170374:19"/>going to ſuffer, are queſtioning, Who ſhould be chiefeſt. Hovv can vve cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>Eſau</hi> for parting vvith his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right at ſo lovv a rate? He vvept vvhen it vvas done; but we do vvorſe, and boaſt of our bargains. O <hi>Judas,</hi> hovv doth our perfidiouſneſſe juſtifie thy higheſt treachery? Thou ſoldeſt thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, yet in a deſperate kinde of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance reſtored'ſt the money: but vve hold it a diſparagement to be over-ſeen in any thing, and vvill venture rather Hell and the Gallovvs to be thought grand Politicians, then to part vvith that vve have once gotten. It vvas a poore content the rich man had of his full barnes, that muſt the ſame night loſe his Soul, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.16. And <hi>Dives</hi> feaſting vvas not vvorth the reckoning, that afforded him not a drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a Grace-cup, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. The Spirit of the Pythoniſſe could preach true Doctrin, Theſe men are the ſervants of the high God, <hi>Acts.</hi> 16. but to bring about a plot, to drive the Apoſtles out of Town, by the infatuated Aldermen that heeded not God, but their gaine. <hi>Rebobohams</hi> brazen ſhields make a ſhew as thoſe of Gold placed in the Temple, by his wiſer father; but, put to the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170374:20"/>touch, the caſe is altered. The Holy Ghoſt may be ſo invocated, that inſtead of a Dove, an Owl may make appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. So, many men talk of gifts, that are but ſhifts; and vaunt of taking pains, who from our Saviour, in the latter day, ſhall have ſmall thanks for their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22. Theſe <hi>Rabſhakehs</hi> will tell us of lands, of corn, and vvine, and olives, and honey, that they will tranſplant us unto, 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 18.32. but it will prove better to adviſe with ſome truſty Iſaiahs, then to preſume too far upon the Gentleman's word. The Woman that upbraided the Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker for want of a ſhoo to fit her foot, was found to have a foot not to be fitted without a miſ-ſhapen ſhoo made on purpoſe. It is dangerous to break ſuch hedges, where a Serpent is like to bite us by the fingers, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.8. and to poure in new vvine into old veſſels that will ſurely break them.</p>
                  <p>Of the three <hi>Teaching Fig-trees</hi> in the Goſpel, the firſt telleth us, that leaves without fruit draw on a curſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. The ſecond, that where dreſſing helps not, it muſt not any longer ſtand to burden the ground, <hi>Luke.</hi> 13. The
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170374:20"/>third, that a day of reckoning is grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. It was too late to gather Mannah, when the Sun had riſen and melted it: and in vain to cry, Lord, Lord, with the fooliſh virgins, when the doores are ſhut, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. Thirſt is a ſigne in Phyſick, that the purgation taken hath well wrought, as it ſhould: My ſoul hath a thirſt for God, yea even for the living God, <hi>when ſhall I come and appear before the preſence of my God?</hi> Pſal. 42.2. My meat, is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his worke, <hi>John.</hi> 4.34. And, <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: for they ſhall be filled, Matthew.</hi> 5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Generation of vipers:</hi> 2. <hi>Sons of Belial:</hi> 3. <hi>Baal Kemarims:</hi> 4. <hi>tongue-men:</hi> 5. <hi>belly-gods:</hi> 6. <hi>curſed lyers, and ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers:</hi> 7. <hi>filthy dreamers, that blaſpheme dignities,</hi> may have their portion here, but ſhall have their potion hereafter, fire and brimſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt; this ſhall be prepared for them, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 11. The Spider weaves a ſubtile web, and watcheth in it diligently to intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle flyes, which he may devour: but when the beeſom of deſtruction com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, behold his travail ſhall come
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170374:21"/>upon his own head, and his wickedneſs on his own pate, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7.17. Muſicians uſually tune their Inſtruments before they play in conſort; and the foot ſhould be looked unto, before we enter into the houſe of God; except we intend to offer the fool's Sacrifice, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. The water of <hi>Siloah,</hi> that runneth ſoftly, will prove better in the end, then the Son of <hi>Remaliah</hi>'s over-flowing torrents. <hi>Every plant that the heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted out, Matthew.</hi> 15.13.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Figures.</head>
                  <p>AS tropicall Speeches conſiſt of choiſe and gracefull Words: So
<note n="*" place="margin">Called by <hi>Cicero, Orationis habitus</hi> from the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, becauſe ſpeech is cloathed and adorned therewith: termed <hi>Figura,</hi> becauſe it giveth a new ſhape, or face to the word, or ſentence, that is embeliſhed, and ſet forth with thoſe flowers. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Plutarch. Figura aneem est, oratio immutata ab co, quod in uſu in conſuetudine poſitum eſt, conſtans fictione quâdam, ornatûs aut utilitatis cauſa. Tully</hi> in <hi>Bruto</hi> divides them in <hi>verberum &amp; ſententiarum lumina,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Figures</hi> ariſe from the fit placing, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or repetition of vvords in Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, vvhich othervviſe vvould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, as homely, or (as may be ſaid) disfigured.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170374:21"/>
                  <p>In this range, are theſe of eſpeciall Note, and Uſe; to which the reſt may be reduced.
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Epizeuxis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Anaphora.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Epistrophe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Epanalepſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Epanados.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. <hi>Paronomaſia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. <hi>Polyptôton.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ab</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ad, et</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>jungere,</hi> becauſe the ſame vvord is adjoyned, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently repeated, therefore termed by <hi>Quintilian, lib.</hi> 9. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Geminatio.</hi> There are three ends of it, put down by him there: 1. for ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as <hi>occidi, occidi; non Sp. Metium,</hi> Wherein the firſt ſerves to ſhew, or demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, the other to affirme: 2. for commiſeration, <hi>Ah Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridon, Coridon:</hi> 3. for elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being joyned with an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony.</note> Epizeuxis.</head>
                  <p>By an <hi>Epizeuxis</hi> the ſame vvord is geminated in the ſame ſentence; in an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, earneſt manner. My <hi>heart is fixed,</hi> O GOD, my <hi>heart is fixed,</hi> I vvill ſing and give praiſe. <hi>Awake</hi> up my glory, <hi>awake</hi> up my lute and harp, I my ſelfe vvill <hi>awake</hi> right early, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 57.7. <hi>O God to whom vengeance belongeth, thou God to whom vengeance belongeth,</hi> ſhevv thy ſelfe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.1. Hovv long ſhall the <hi>wicked?</hi> Hovv long ſhall the <hi>wicked</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph? Hovv long ſhall they utter, and ſpeak hard things, and make ſuch proud boaſting? <hi>Ib.</hi> For theſe things I vveep, <hi>mine eye, mine eye,</hi> runneth dovvn vvith vvater: becauſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170374:22"/>that ſhould relieve my Soul, is far from me, my Children are deſolate, becauſe the Enemy prevailed, <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.16. So, O <hi>earth, earth, earth,</hi> hear the vvord of the Lord, <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> 22.29. <hi>A ſword, a ſword,</hi> is ſharpned and alſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhed: it is ſharpned to make a ſore ſlaughter, it is furbiſhed that it may glitter, ſhould vve then make mirth? It contemneth the rod of my Son, as every tree, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.9, 10. I vvill <hi>overturne, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturne, overturne it,</hi> and it ſhall be no more untill he come, vvhoſe right it is, and I vvill give it him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.27. In the ſame ſtraine are theſe of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; <hi>Martha, Martha,</hi> thou art carefull and troubled about many things, but one thing is neceſſary, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.41, 42. <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killest the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy Children together, as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings, but ye would not,</hi> Matth. 23, 37. Luk. 13.34. <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, multitudes</hi> in the valley of deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the day of the Lord is neer in the valley of <hi>deciſion, Joel.</hi> 3.14. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, a Parentheſis is interpoſed, as They ſeemed to be <hi>ſomewhat</hi> (vvhatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they vvere, it maketh no matter to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170374:22"/>me, God accepteth no mans perſon) for they who ſeemed to be <hi>ſomewhat</hi> in conference added nothing to me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.6.</p>
                  <p>To this Epizeuxis, may be referred
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reduplicatie,</hi> called by <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Verbi ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem repetitio à</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>dicere; quia idem ſonus iteratur.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Anadiploſis,</hi> which is when the ſame word, that ends one ſentence, begins the other: and <hi>Climax,</hi> a climbing by a repetition of the words before, to make as it were a foot-ſtep to aſcend higher, as both words give it. I was glad when they ſaid unto me, We will go into the houſe of the Lord; our feet ſhall ſtand within thy gates O <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. Jeruſalem</hi> is built as a City that is at unity in it ſelfe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 122.1.2. I will laugh at your calamity, and I will mock when your <hi>feare</hi> cometh; when your <hi>feare</hi> cometh as deſolation, and your deſtruction cometh as a whirl-wind; when diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon you, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.26.27. And it ſhall come to paſſe when they ſhall ſay unto thee, Whither ſhall we go forth? then thou ſhalt tell them, Thus ſaith the Lord, Such as are for <hi>Death,</hi> to <hi>death;</hi> and ſuch as are for the <hi>Sword,</hi> to the <hi>ſword;</hi> and ſuch as are for <hi>Famine,</hi> to the <hi>famine;</hi> and ſuch as are for <hi>Captivity,</hi> to the <hi>captivity, Jer.</hi> 15.2. So, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.9.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170374:23"/>That which <hi>Dyeth,</hi> let it <hi>dye,</hi> and that that is <hi>Cut off,</hi> let it be <hi>cut off,</hi> and let the reſt <hi>cut</hi> every one the fleſh of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>ſcala, gradus,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, becauſe in this figure we do proceed as it were by certain ſteps, or rounds in a ladder: whence it is named <hi>Gradatio; repetit quae dictaſunt, &amp; priuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ad aliud deſcendat, in prioribus reſistit.</hi> Quintil. L. 9. c. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Climax,</hi> theſe nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concatenations we have in the New Teſtament, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call upon the name of the Lord ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: How then ſhal they call on him, in whom they have not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved? and how ſhal they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they heare without a Preacher? and how ſhall they Preach, except they be ſent?</hi> Rom. 10.13, 14, 15. <hi>Whom he did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know, he alſo did praedeſtinate to be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the image of his Son, that he might be the firſt born among many brethren. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over whom he did praedeſtinate, them he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called; whom he called, them he alſo juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and whom he juſtified, he alſo glorified,</hi> Rom. 8.29. <hi>We glory in tribulation, knowing that tribulation worketh patience, and patience experience, and experience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3.4, 5. Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all diligence, add to your <hi>faith vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170374:23"/>and to virtue Knowledge, and to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Temperance, and to temperance Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and to patience Godlineſſe, and to godlineſſe Brotherly kindneſſe, and to bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindneſſe Charity,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.5, 6, 7. In which kind is that ſaying, Learn to know, know to doe, doe to dye, dye to live, live to laud. So as by <hi>Higgaions, Selahs, Hoſannahs,</hi> we may attaine at length to coeleſtiall <hi>Halleluichs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">By <hi>Plutarch</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and by him taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of to be very powerfull to work upon the affections as well as to delight the care; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>quare videtur eſſe adhibenda &amp; ad exornandam, &amp; augendam orationem. Auth. ad Heren.</hi>
                     </note> Anaphora.</head>
                  <p>In <hi>Anaphora</hi> the ſame word is re-aſſum'd to begin divers ſentences. So bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and curſings, are Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically propounded. <hi>If ye walke in my ſtatutes,</hi> and keep my Commandements, and do them, <hi>I will give you</hi> raine in due ſeaſon, — <hi>I will give</hi> peace in the land, — <hi>I will</hi> have reſpect unto you, — <hi>I will</hi> ſet my Tabernacle amongſt you. — But, if ye will not hearken unto me, but walke contrary to me, then <hi>will I</hi> walke alſo contrary to you, in fury; <hi>and I, even I, will</hi> haſtiſe you 7 times for your ſins, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.3.27, 28. In like manner, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Bleſſed, bleſſed, bleſſed,</hi> —
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170374:24"/>and, <hi>Curſed, curſed, curſed,</hi> — are re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by Anaphora, as the 8 Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and ſo many Woes are pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and denounced to the Happy, and Hypocrites, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. &amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 23. In the ſame figure, Charity is diſplayed; <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> ſuffereth long, and is kind; <hi>Charity</hi> envieth not, <hi>Charity</hi> vaunteth not her ſelfe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. The abhominations of the bloody City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in their power to ſhed blood, are heavily taxed. <hi>In thee</hi> have they ſet light by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother; in the midſt <hi>of thee,</hi> have they dealt by oppreſſions, with the ſtranger; <hi>in thee</hi> have they vexed the fatherleſs and the widow. Thou haſt deſpiſed my holy things, and profaned my Sabbaths; <hi>in thee</hi> are men, that carry tales to ſhed blood; <hi>in thee</hi> they that eat upon the mountaines; in the midſt <hi>of thee,</hi> they commit lewdneſſe; <hi>in thee,</hi> have they diſcovered their fathers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe; <hi>in thee,</hi> have they humbled her that was ſet a part for pollution, and one hath committed abhomination with his neighbours wife, and another hath lewdly defiled his daughter in law, and another <hi>in thee</hi> hath humbled his Siſter, his Fathers daughter; <hi>in thee</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170374:24"/>have they taken gifts to ſhed blood; <hi>thou</hi> haſt taken uſury, and encreaſe, and <hi>thou</hi> haſt greedily gained of thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by extortion, and haſt forgotten me, ſaith the Lord God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.7. The devaſtations of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the Prophet, <hi>Mine</hi> eyes fail with teares, <hi>My</hi> bowels are troubled, <hi>My</hi> liver is poured upon the earth for the deſtruction of the daughter of my people? <hi>What thing</hi> ſhall I take to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for thee? <hi>what thing</hi> ſhall I liken to thee, O daughter of <hi>Jeruſalem? what</hi> ſhall I equall to thee? that I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee, O virgin daughter of Sion, for thy breach is great like the Sea, who can heal thee? <hi>Lament.</hi> 2.11.13. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Gods people may be worried, and vilified as trampled droſſe, yet God profeſſeth, He will make them his battle-axe, and weapons of War:
<note place="margin">Jer. 51.20, 21, 22.</note> For <hi>with thee</hi> (ſaith he) will I break in pieces the Nations, and <hi>with thee</hi> will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Kingdomes, and <hi>with thee</hi> will I break in pieces the horſe, and his rider, and <hi>with thee</hi> will I break in pieces the Chariot, and his rider; <hi>with thee</hi> alſo will I break in pieces man and woman, and <hi>with thee</hi> will I break in pieces old and young, and <hi>with thee</hi> will I break in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170374:25"/>pieces the young Man, and the Maid. I will alſo break in pieces <hi>with thee,</hi> the Shepheard and his flock, and <hi>with thee</hi> will I break in pieces the husbandman and his yoak of oxen; and <hi>with thee</hi> will I break in pieces Captains and Rulers, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.20. What went ye out into the wilderneſſe to ſee? three times aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.7. The 11th Chapter to the Hebrews is a continued Anaphora by reſuming the word, <hi>By Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rutilius</hi> calleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Hermogenes</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Cicero <hi>Converſio, quid ad postremum continenter revertimur. Auth. ad Heren.</hi>
                     </note> Epiſtrophe.</head>
                  <p>That elegancy which A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naphora acquires by repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame words in the beginning, <hi>Epiſtrophe</hi> equalls, by doing the like in the concluſion, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one the other: Ye houſe of Iſrael, put your truſt in the Lord; <hi>He is their ſuccour and defender.</hi> Ye houſe of Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, put your truſt in the Lord; <hi>He is their ſuccour and defender, Pſal.</hi> 115. So, <hi>His mercy endureth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 136. twenty and ſeven times repeated. To which Figure may be referred that of our Saviour, This is the Father's will which hath ſent me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170374:25"/>
                     <hi>but ſhould raiſe it up again at the laſt day.</hi> And this is the will of him that ſent me, that every one which ſeeth and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him, may have everlaſting life, <hi>and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> No man can come to me, except the Father which hath ſent me draw him, <hi>and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day, Joh.</hi> 6. Likewiſe that, If thy hand offend thee, cut it off; it is better for thee to enter into life maimed, then having two hands to go <hi>into hell, into the fire that never ſhall be quenched.</hi> And if thy foot offend thee, cut it off; for it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for thee to enter in halt into life, then having two feet to be caſt <hi>into hell, into the fire that never ſhall be quenched; where the worm dyeth not, and the fire is not quenched.</hi> And if thy eye offend thee, pluck it out; it is better for thee to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdom of God with one eye, than having two eyes to be caſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell fire, where the worm dyeth not, and the fire is not quenched, Mar.</hi> 9. So, of myſticall <hi>Babylon</hi>'s ruine it is ſaid, The voice of harpers, and muſitians, and pipers, and trumpeters, ſhall be heard no more at all <hi>in thee.</hi> And no crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of whatſoever craft ſhall be found any more at all <hi>in thee;</hi> and the ſound
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170374:26"/>of the mill-ſtone ſhall be heard no more at all <hi>in thee,</hi> and the light of a candle ſhall ſhine no more at all <hi>in thee,</hi> and the voice of the bride-groom ſhall be heard no more at all <hi>in thee, Rev.</hi> 18.22.</p>
                  <p>Under Epiſtrophe may be compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<note n="*" place="margin">Commoratio, <hi>quia in loco firmiſſimo, que tota cauſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinetur, monetur diutiùs, &amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſaepiùs reditur: nam &amp; commoratio in una re permul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm movet.</hi> Cicer. de orat. <hi>Epimone eſt Tropus in theologiâ quando dictio repetitur ad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem certitudinem, vel defide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii expreſſionem, ut,</hi> Amen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>dico-vobis. Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i. unt quod ſit, quando dictio non tota repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur ſed principium &amp; finis va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur, ut, Expectando expectavi. Vetus Vocabularius.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Epimone,</hi> When a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, as it were the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of a ſong, is often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated; as that, <hi>Turn us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, thou God of hoſts, ſhew us the light of thy countenance and we ſhall be whole,</hi> thrice repeated <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. So, <hi>Why art thou ſo vexed, O my ſoul, and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? O put thy truſt in God — Pſal.</hi> 42.11. So that paſſage, <hi>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the wonders that he doth for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, Pſal.</hi> 107. four times repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. As that, <hi>For all that, his anger is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill, Iſa.</hi> 9. So that of our Saviour to his Diſciples, <hi>He that loveth father or mother more then me is not worthy of me,</hi> thrice repeated, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37. And ſo, —<hi>receive a reward, Ib.</hi> 41. In the ſame
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170374:26"/>ſtrain is that, <hi>Charity beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7.</p>
                  <p>From Anaphora and Epiſtrophe joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, ariſeth
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Complicatio,</hi> becauſe both the former Figures are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and wrapt in this. <hi>Cum repetitio fit in principiis &amp; clauſulis.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploce,</hi> as, O give thanks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord <hi>for he is grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, becauſe his mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever.</hi> Let Iſrael now confeſſe that <hi>he is gratious, and that his mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever.</hi> Let the houſe of Aaron now confeſſe, that <hi>his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> Yea, let all them that fear the Lord confeſſe, that <hi>his mercy endureth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 118.2, 3, 4. No man of us <hi>liveth to himſelf, and no man dyeth to himſelf; for whether we live, we live to the Lord, or whether we die, we die to the Lord: Whether we live therefore or die, we are the Lords, Rom.</hi> 14.7, 8. <hi>We know in part, we propheſy in part; but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be done away. When I was a child I ſpake as a child, I underſtood as a child, I thought as a child; but when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a man, I put away childiſh things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10.11. A ſtupendious Symploce is that, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32. Aſhur is there, and all her company: <hi>his graves are about him, all of them ſlain, fallen by
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170374:27"/>the ſword, whoſe graves are ſet in the ſide of the pit, and her company is round about her grave; all of them ſlain, fallen by the ſword.</hi> There is Elam and her multitude <hi>round about her grave, all of them ſlain, fallen by the ſword, which are gone down uncircumciſed unto the neather parts of the earth, which cauſed their terrour in the land of the living, yet have they born their ſhame with them that go down into the pit—</hi> So, <hi>There is Meſech, Tubal, Edom, the Princes of the north, and all the Sidonians, in the ſame poſture.</hi> More pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall is that of <hi>Obadiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Obad. 1.13.</note> Thou ſhouldſt not have entred into the gate of my people <hi>in the day of their calamity;</hi> nor laid hands on their ſubſtance <hi>in the day of their calamity.</hi> To this may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that ſtrain of our Saviour, <hi>If ye love them that love you, what thanks have ye? for ſinners alſo love thoſe that love them. And if ye do good to them which do good to you, what thanks have ye? for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners alſo do even the ſame. And if ye lend to them of whom ye hope to receive, what thanks have ye? for ſinners alſo lend to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to receive as much again, Luk.</hi> 6. So, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.34. <hi>Two— the one ſhall be taken and the other left;</hi> thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170374:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reſumptio, quando primis reſpondent ultima.</hi> Quintilian. <hi>Author ad</hi> Heren. <hi>vocat Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duplicationem, cùm ratione am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plificationis, aut commiſerationis cjuſdem unius, aut plurium ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum fit iteratio.</hi>
                     </note> Epanalepſis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epanalepſis</hi> ends with the ſame word it begins. For we are ſaved by <hi>hope;</hi> but <hi>hope</hi> that is ſeen is not <hi>hope, Rom.</hi> 8.24. <hi>Rejoyce</hi> in the Lord, and again I ſay, <hi>Rejoyce, Phil.</hi> 4.4. So Pſalm the 8th beginneth with, <hi>O Lord our governour, how excellent is thy name in all the world?</hi> and ends with the ſame words. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. hath this beginning, <hi>Praiſe the Lord, all my ſoul;</hi> and endeth in the ſame words, termed, The Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors round. <hi>As we ſaid before, ſo ſay I now again, If any man preach any other goſpell unto you then ye have received, let him be accurſed.</hi> Inferred upon the ſaying before, <hi>Though we or an Angel from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven preach any other goſpel unto you than ye have received, let him be accurſed, Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170374:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Regreſſio, ſen Reditio in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Plutarch: <hi>Quando duas res, &amp; nomina proponens aliquis, ſenſu nondum finito, redit ad utrumque nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ut compleat ſententiae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum, ut, — Divellimur inde Iphitus &amp; Pelias mecum; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Iphitus aevo Jam gravior—</hi>
                     </note> Epanados.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epanados</hi> reſumes that which was ſpoken, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſeth it with an explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ringing, as it were, the ſame Bells in changes: The ungodly have drawn <hi>out the ſword,</hi> and bent <hi>the bow,</hi> to caſt down the poor and needy, and to ſlay ſuch as be of a right converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Their <hi>ſword</hi> ſhall God throw through their own heart, and their <hi>bowe</hi> ſhall be broken, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.14, 15. Woe unto thee that <hi>ſpoileſt,</hi> and waſt not ſpoyled; and <hi>dealeſt treacherouſly,</hi> and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee. When thou ſhalt ceaſe to <hi>ſpoil,</hi> thou ſhalt be ſpoiled; and when thou ſhalt make an end to <hi>deal treacherouſly,</hi> they ſhall deal treacherouſly with thee, <hi>Eſay</hi> 33.1. When the holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, he ſhall reprove the world <hi>of ſin, of righteouſneſſe,</hi> and of <hi>judgment.</hi> Of <hi>ſin,</hi> becauſe they believe not on me; of <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> becauſe I go to the Father, and ye ſee me no more: of <hi>judgment,</hi> becauſe the prince of this world is judged, <hi>John</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170374:28"/>16.8, 9, 10, 11. The <hi>Jewes</hi> require a ſigne, and the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſeek after wiſdom; but we preach Chriſt crucified; to the <hi>Jewes</hi> a ſtumbling-block, and unto the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſſe; but unto them which are called, both <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Greeks,</hi> Chriſt the power of God, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Becauſe the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men, and the weakneſſe of God is ſtronger then men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Agnominatio, alluſio Vocis ad vocem, quae fit per literae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, detractiunem, tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitionem, vel immutationem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nt, Amantes ſunt amentes. Raras das mihi literas; charas tamen.</note> Paronomaſia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paronomaſia</hi> ſeaſonably uſed, delights the hearers, helps the memory, and ſhewes, in propinquity of words, the difference of things. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I have taken upon me to ſpeak unto the Lord, which am but <hi>apher</hi> and <hi>epher,</hi> duſt and aſhes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.27. As for the gods of the heathens, they be but idols; their <hi>Elohim</hi> are <hi>elilim, Pſal.</hi> 96.5. <hi>Diis, noddys,</hi> their idols <hi>addle, idle</hi> in Engliſh expreſſion. In the mountain [of the Church] the Lord of hoſtes ſhall make unto all people <hi>miſhteh ſhemanim,</hi> a feaſt of fat things; <hi>miſhteh ſhemarim,</hi> feaſts of wine in the lees, <hi>Eſa,</hi> 25.6.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170374:29"/>wherein ſhall be the complement of marrow-diſhes, and brisk pure wine, which ſhall ſatisfie the utmoſt ſpiritual appetite. So, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, envy and murder; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and wickedneſſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, without underſtanding, covenant-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.29.31. have a colour of Paronomaſia, which will ſavour of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantiſm to be too often uſed. In the eighth of <hi>Amos, verſ.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>Kaits</hi> uſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in <hi>Keets;</hi> plenty, deſtruction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>multum; &amp;</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o, quaſi dicas, Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um carietatem, cùm ejuſdem nominis caſus ſapiùs commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>antur,</hi> Cicer. <hi>ad</hi> Brut. <hi>Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur haec caſihus &amp; generibus i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                                 <desc>••…</desc>
                              </gap>, under</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> Quint <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> variorum caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                                 <desc>••…</desc>
                              </gap>dem f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nte deductorum, ut</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>d <hi>Metamorph. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Heu quantum ſcelus eſt in viſcere viſcera condi,</l>
                           <l>Congeſto<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> avidum pingueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere corpore corpus.</l>
                           <l>Alteriuſque animantem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantis vivere lethol</l>
                           <l>Called by the Author <hi>ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. Traductio,</hi> by others <hi>Me</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </note> Polyptoton.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Polyptoton</hi> inculcates ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently, in divers caſes and expreſſions, what we would have notice to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken eſpecially of. Jeſhurun <hi>waxed fat</hi> and kicked. <hi>Thou art waxen fat, thou art thick, thou art covered with fatneſſe.</hi> Then he forſook God which made him, and lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the rock of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15. Hath he <hi>ſmitten</hi> him as he <hi>ſmote</hi> thoſe that <hi>ſmote</hi> him? or, is he <hi>flain</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>ſlaughter</hi> of them which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170374:29"/>are <hi>ſlain</hi> by him? <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.7. No, in meaſure. God will deal more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with his, then his enemies. When it ſhouteth forth he will debate with it, and ſtay his <hi>rough wind</hi> in the day of his <hi>eaſt wind,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14. Bleſſed be God, the <hi>Father</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>Father</hi> of mercies, and God of all <hi>comfort,</hi> who <hi>comforteth</hi> us in all our tribulation, that we may be able to <hi>comfort</hi> them which are in any trouble, by the <hi>comfort</hi> wherewith we our ſelves are <hi>comforted</hi> of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The ſabbath was made for man, not man for the ſabbath; therefore the Son of man is Lord alſo of the ſabbath, Mar.</hi> 2.27, 28. For he hath made him to be <hi>ſin</hi> for us who knew no <hi>ſin,</hi> that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
                  <p>The combining of theſe Figures to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the former Tropes, carry with them a delightfull and winning grace, eſpecially in 1 petitions; 2 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; 3 quick reproofs or encite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. So, (1) that of the Apoſtle, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God I how unſearchable are his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170374:30"/>judgments, and his waies paſt finding out? For who hath known the minde of the Lord? or who hath been his counſellor? or who hath first given to him, and it ſhall be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced to him again? For in him, and through him, and to him are all things, to whom be glory for ever. Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>My God, my God look upon me. Why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me, and art ſo far from my health, and from the word of my complaint? Pſal.</hi> 22.1. <hi>O God my heart is ready, my heart is ready; I will ſing and give praiſe with the beſt member that I have, Pſal.</hi> 18.1. (2.) A complaint ſtudded with ſuch ſparkling gems, we have, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. (3.) Quick ſpeeches, called by the Preacher, <hi>goads and nails, faſtned by the maſters of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.11. come under this reckoning. As, Our Saviour turned wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into wine to ſupply the new mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried's wants; but we turn wine into water out of luxurious wantonneſſe. If St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s ſucceſſor were ſtinted to his founder's allowance, <hi>Silver and gold have I none;</hi> he would quickly be weary of the Chair, which hath ſo ſcant a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Both ſorts of thoſe fanaticks are to blame, as well thoſe that will have no ſet prayers, as thoſe that will have no prayers but ſet. God makes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170374:30"/>Proteſtants, but the Papiſts make god. Religion makes us, but they make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and this made-religion they maintain, that this maintained may maintain them. We ſhould as well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to Chriſts merits, that ſo his merits might be rather a ſtay to our infirmities, then a ſtale to our enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. We muſt therefore couple faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe with faith, that we may do, as well as believe, and that becauſe we do believe. We muſt take heed, that whilſt we hunt after neat expreſſions,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Col. 2.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, 1 Cor. 1.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Ib c.</hi> 7.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>unde</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Epheſ. 5.6.</note> we let not ſlip the thing that ſhould be chiefly preſſed and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Divers aim to ſhew, how much they can ſay on a Text, with no regard at all how little their auditors can bear away; as though they came into a Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit to open onely their ſtore, not to feed their flocks; and to beg applauſe of their Congregation, that they are ready Preachers, not to ſo lead them that they may be profitable hearers. Such ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding braſſe is not fit metal to make veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels for the Temple; and ſuch tinckling cymballs, without ſolidity and charity, make fit muſick for a May-pole. Theſe ſycophanticall ſermonings, angling for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170374:31"/>gain, more then ſouls; and applauſe, more then the proficiency of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, the Apoſtle calls God to witneſs, was far from his manner of teaching, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>quia af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus ſeu motus animi iſtas Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiarum figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras praecipué ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur. Differt Sententiae figura à figura Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quòd illa ſententias illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minet, in figuris autem dictionis aptè &amp; jucundè inter ſe reſonent: deinde quòd ſententiarum conformationes mutatis verbis confistere poſſunt; Figurae autem dictionis non item, quia mutatis ſedibus perit reſonantia, quâ fit color.</hi>
                     </note> Of Schemes.</head>
                  <p>TO teach, to delight, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to perſwade, are the ſcopes of Oratory. After teaching-Tropes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and delighting-Figures, convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and perſwading-<hi>Schemes</hi> may be well enquired after.</p>
                  <p>Theſe come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the titles of
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Ecphoneſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Epanorthoſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Apoſtrophe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Proſopopoea.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Aporia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. <hi>Anacoinoſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. <hi>Synchoreſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170374:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Exclamatio,</hi> becauſe in the pronountiation there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a ſtraining and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the voice, the ſigne of which is either ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb or Interjection. <hi>Ecce quàm bonum &amp; quàm jucundum habitare fratres in unum!</hi> Pſal. 133. <hi>O proſundas divitias tum ſapientiae, tum cognitionis Dei! quàm inſcrutabilia ſunt ejus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicia, &amp; ejus viae imperveſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles?</hi> Rom. 11.35.</note> Ecphoneſis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ecphoneſis,</hi> or exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are raiſed upon ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious occaſions, that they can hardly be confined; moſt fall within compaſſe of theſe limits: 1. Of <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring,</hi> How is the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full city become an harlot! It was full of judgment, righteouſneſſe lodged in it, but now murderers. Thy ſilver is become droſſe,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.21.</note> thy wine mixt with water. 2. <hi>Wiſhing;</hi> O that they (Gods people) were wiſe, that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end! <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. O that my people would have hearkened unto me! If Iſrael had walked in my waies, I ſhould have ſoon put down their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and turned my hand againſt their adverſaries. The haters of the Lord ſhould have been found lyers. Alſo with the fineſt wheat-flower, and with hony out of the ſtony-rock, ſhould I have ſatisfied thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.15, 16. O that thou wouldeſt rend the heavens, that thou wouldeſt come down, that the mountains might flow down at thy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170374:32"/>preſence, as when the fire of melting burneth,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.</note> the fire that cauſeth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to boil, to make thy name known to thine adverſaries. 3. <hi>Complaining:</hi> O Lord, what ſhall I ſay, when Iſrael turn their backs before their enemies? for the Canaanites and all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the land ſhall hear of it, and ſhall environ us round, and cut off our name from the earth, and what wilt thou do unto thy great name? <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.8. O God, wherefore art thou abſent from us ſo long? why is thy wrath ſo hot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſheep of thy paſture? O think upon thy congregation whom thou haſt purchaſed, and redeemed of old. Think upon the tribe of thine inheritance, and mount Sion wherein thou haſt dwelt. Lift up thy feet, that thou maiſt utterly deſtroy every enemy, which hath done evill in thy ſanctuary, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. O wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am!
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> who ſhall deliver me from this body of death? 4. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</hi> O generation of Vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come? <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7. O faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and perverſe generation, how long ſhall I be with you? how long ſhall I ſuffer you? <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.17. O fools and ſlow of heart to believe all that the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170374:32"/>Prophets have ſpoken? <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.25. Ye ſtiff-necked and uncircumciſed in hearts and ears; ye do alwaies reſiſt the holy Ghoſt; as your fathers did, ſo do ye, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. O full of ſubtlety and all miſchief, thou child of the devill,
<note place="margin">Act. 13.10.</note> thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe, wilt you not ceaſe to pervert the wayes of the Lord? 5. <hi>Exſultation.</hi> Behold how good and joyfull a thing it is for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell together in unity! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.1. What reward ſhall I give unto the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.11.</note> for all the benefits he hath done unto me? 6. <hi>Inſultation.</hi> How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer ſon of the morning! How art thou caſt down to the ground, which didſt weaken the nations! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.12. O thou enemy! de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions are come to a perpetuall end,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.6.</note> even of the Cityes which thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, their memorial is periſhed with them. 7. <hi>Commiſeration.</hi> Ah Lord God! wilt thou deſtroy all the reſidue of Iſraell in pouring out of thy fury upon Jeruſalem? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.8. Behold O Lord, and conſider to whom thou haſt done this! ſhall the women eat their fruit, and children of a ſpan long? ſhall the Prieſt and the Prophet be ſlaine in the Sanctuary of the Lord! <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170374:33"/>
                  <p>To this Exclamation may be referred an
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rei narratae, vel probatae ſumma acclamatio.</hi> Quint. <hi>ut, Tantae molis erat Romanam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere gentem Ad ditur ad finem, fine exclamationis notâ.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> or ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious cloſure, relating to premiſes of conſequence: Thus they provoked him to anger with their owne inventions, and the plague was great amongſt them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.29. Thus were they ſtain'd with their owne works, and went a whoring after their own inventions. <hi>ib.</hi> 38. Thus they turned the glory of God into the ſimilitude of a calfe that eateth hey. <hi>Ib.</hi> 20. Thus Joaſh the King remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not the kindneſſe which <hi>Jehojada</hi> his father had done unto him, but ſlew his ſon; and vvhen he died, he ſaid, The Lord look upon it, and require it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Quaſi <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Libertas loquendi.</note> 
                     <hi>Parrheſia,</hi> an aſſumed freedom of ſpeech, vvhich is commonly uſhered in, vvith an excuſing praeface. Men and brethren let me freely ſpeak unto you of the patriarch <hi>David,</hi> that he is both dead, and buried, and his ſepulcher vvith us this day, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.29. We cannot but ſpeak the things vvhich vve have both ſeen, and heard. <hi>Ib.</hi> 4.20. the King knoweth of theſe things, before whom I ſpeak, [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>freely.</hi> For I am perſwaded, that none of theſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170374:33"/>things are hidden from him; for this thing was not done in a corner, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Correctio, quae tollit id quod dictum eſt; &amp;, pro eo, id quod magis idoneum videtur, reponit. Author. ad Heren.</hi> Called by the Greeks likewiſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Epanorthoſis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epanorthoſis</hi> doth in ſome ſort qualifie that, which hath, as we make it, ſlipped from us; or drowneth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, which we would have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, though not uttered. Can a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb? Yea, they may forget, yet will not I forget thee, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.15. Father, ſave me from this hour; but for this cauſe came I into the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.27. I laboured more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then they all; yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. I marvell that you are ſo ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from him that called you into the grace of Chriſt, unto another Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which is not another. But there be ſome that trouble you, and would pervert the goſpell of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6, 7.</p>
                  <p>Attendant to this is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reticentia,</hi> Cicer. <hi>Obticen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Celſus.</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by others, <hi>Interruptio,</hi> becauſe the thred of diſcourſe is broken off. Virgil. <hi>Quos ego: ſed motos praeſtat componere fluctus.</hi> Uſed 1. To expreſſe anger; <hi>Quem quidem ego ſi ſenſero: ſed quid opus eſt verbis,</hi> Plaut. 2. Fear: Virgil. <hi>Neque vincere certo: Quanquam O: ſed ſuperent quibus hoe, Neptune, dedisti.</hi> 3. An high paſſion of grief: <hi>Tu autem Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova quouſque!</hi> Pſal. 6.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Apoſiopeſis,</hi> when ſomewhat is left to be gathered,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170374:34"/>by a breaking off abruptly. Oh this people have ſinned a great ſin, and made them gods of gold: yet now if thou wilt forgive them their ſin [It is too much for me to ask, but thy infinite mercy may afford it]: if not, blot me out, I pray thee, of the book which thou haſt written, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. To whom I ſware in my wrath, [if they ſhould enter into my reſt] left to be underſtood, Let not me be truſted any more upon oath. If thou hadſt known, even at leaſt in this thy day the things which belong unto thy peace, (thou wouldſt have taken better courſes, or the like): but now they are hid from thine eyes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Averſio, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo averſus;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſcene of ſpeech is changed and directed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</note> Apoſtrophe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apoſtrophe,</hi> in a continuate ſpeech, turns from the hearers, or matter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and beſpeaks a thing or perſon abſent, or preſent, by the By. So <hi>David,</hi> in lamenting the death of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi> lets fly an imprecation upon the place where they were ſlain: Ye moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> let there be no dew,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170374:34"/>nor let there be rain upon you, nor fields of offerings; for there the ſhield of the Mighty is vilely caſt away, the ſhield of <hi>Saul,</hi> as though he had not been annointed with oyle, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. So, in declaring <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s exodus from <hi>Egypt,</hi> he beſpeaks the ſea, and <hi>Jordan,</hi> with the mountains, and earth it ſelf: What aileth thee, O thou ſea, that thou fleddeſt! &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114.5. So <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> makes the heavens and earth his auditors; Hear, O heaven, and give ear, O earth, for the Lord hath ſpoken. I have nouriſhed and brought up chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and they have rebelled againſt me, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. Baldneſſe is come upon <hi>Gaza, Askalon</hi> is cut off with the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of their valley; how long wilt thou cut thy ſelf? O thou ſword of the Lord, how long will it be ere thou be quiet? Put up thy ſelf into thy ſcabbard; reſt, and be ſtill, <hi>Jer.</hi> 47.6. In the 24th <hi>Pſalm;</hi> upon profeſſion, that although The earth be the Lords, with all the fulneſſe, and inhabitants of the world; yet becauſe all have not that ſhare in it as the Iſraelites, (God's favourites) <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.14, 15; the Prophet breaks out, by an high Apoſtrophe, to the Gates, for enlarging themſelves, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170374:35"/>the Ark of God: Lift up your heads, O ye gates; and be ye lift up, ye everlaſting doors; and the King of glory ſhall come in. Twice repeated; that the compellation of the ſenſleſſe gates might make the deeper impreſſion, for opening to Chriſt knocking at the door of our hearts. And this ſort of Apoſtrophe to ſenſſeſſe creatures, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten met with in other Authors. But two other beſides, the one to God, the other to our own ſouls, are peculiar in a manner to Scripture-Rhetorick. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtrophe to God, 1. by <hi>Petition.</hi> 2. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</hi> 3. <hi>Praiſes.</hi> 4. <hi>Thankſgiving.</hi> 5. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of oppoſites.</hi> 6. <hi>Stirring up our ſelves.</hi> 7. <hi>Inciting others, and inviting.</hi> Thus, upon a narration of Gods won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull conducting the Iſraelites out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Prophet raiſeth a moſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall Apoſtrophe. Look down from heaven, and behold from the habitation of thy holineſſe, and of thy glory. Where is thy zeal, and thy ſtrength, the ſounding of thy bowells and thy mercies, towards me are they reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? — Doubtleſſe, thou art our Father — O Lord, why haſt thou made us to erre from thy waies, and hardened our hearts from thy fear?
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170374:35"/>by leaving us to putrifie in our own corruptions). O that thou wouldeſt rend the heavens — Behold, thou art wroth, for we have ſinned? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. Such are thoſe of bleſſed King <hi>Charles,</hi> worthy of all imitation. Apoſtrophe to our own ſelves are termed <hi>Solilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies,</hi> ſeldom found out of Scripture. So, The river of <hi>Kiſhon</hi> ſwept them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that antient river, the river of <hi>Kiſhon.</hi> O my ſoul, thou haſt trodden down ſtrength, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.21. In ſuch a Soliloquy, <hi>David</hi> cheareth up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Why art thou ſo vexed, O my ſoul, and why art thou ſo diſquieted in me? O put thy truſt in God, for I will yet thank him, which is the help of my countenance and my God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.14. So, Praiſe the Lord, O my ſoul, and all that is within me praiſe his holy name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. So, 104. Praiſe the Lord, O my ſoul. Thus he doth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and makes Apoſtrophe's to others to do the like; O come let us ſing unto the Lord — Sing unto the Lord a new ſong— So, all former Halleluiahs are ſhut up with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe to all, Let every thing that hath breath praiſe the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170374:36"/>
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Fictio perſonae,</hi> when the perſon is not there, but brought in upon the ſtage ſpeaking as if he were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. So a thing that is mute oft-times, is dreſſed up in a perſon, and words put in his mouth. In this, there ought to be a decorum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that ye dreſſe not the ſervant like the maſter, but that there be a reſpect had to the thing perſonated, and accordingly to be clothed with words, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22.</note> Proſopopoea.</head>
                  <p>By a <hi>Proſopopoea,</hi> 1. <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is filled with a ſpeech; How long, ye ſimple ones, will ye love ſimplicity, and the ſcorners delight in their ſcorning, and fools hate knowledge? Turn at my reproof: behold, I will pour out my ſpirit unto you, I wil make knovvn my words unto you. 2. A <hi>Harlot;</hi> I have peace-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings with me this day, I have payed my vowes. Therefore come I forth to meet thee diligently, to ſeek thy face; and I have found thee. I have decked my bed with coverings of tapeſtry, with carved work, vvith fine linnen of <hi>Egypt.</hi> I have perfumed my bed vvith myrrh,
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.</note> aloes, and cynnamon. Come, let us take our fill of love untill the morning, let us ſolace our ſelves with love. For the good man is not at home, he is gone a long journey; he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a bag of mony with him, and will come at the day appointed. 3. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Church-robbers:</hi> Come let us root them out, that they be no more a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170374:36"/>people, and that the name of Iſrael may be no more in remembrance.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.4.</note> 4. <hi>Hypocriticall Separatiſts,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 65.5.</note> that walk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own thoughts. Stand by thy ſelf, come not near to me; for I am ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier then thou. 5. <hi>Rebells;</hi> For now they will ſay, We have no King, becauſe vve feared not the Lord,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 10.</note> vvhat then ſhould a King do to us? They have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vvords, ſvvearing falſly in making a covenant. Thus judgment ſpringeth up like hemlock in the furrows of the field. The inhabitants of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſhall fear, becauſe of the calves of <hi>Beth aven.</hi> 6. <hi>Wretched Nabals:</hi> What ſhall I do? I have no room to beſtovv my fruits. This vvill I do,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.17, 18, 19.</note> I vvill pull dovvn my barns and build greater, and there vvill I beſtovv my fruits and my goods. And I vvill ſay to my ſoul, Soul, thou haſt much goods laid up for many years, Take thine eaſe, eat, and drink, and be merry. 7. <hi>Penitent Prodigals:</hi> How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hired ſervants of my fathers, have bread enough and to ſpare, and I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh vvith hunger? I vvill ariſe and go to my father and ſay to him, Father, I have ſinned againſt heaven and againſt thee, and am no more vvorthy to be called thy ſon, make me as one of thy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170374:37"/>hired ſervants, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.17, 18, 19. In like manner the Phariſee and Publican are fitted vvith prayers, <hi>Ib.</hi> 18.11, 12, 13. And the deſperate, vvith a ſpeech con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to their remedileſſe caſe: This vvas he vvhom vve had ſometimes in deriſion, and a proverb; We fools ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted his life madneſſe, and his end vvithout honour. Hovv is he numbered among the children of God, and his life among the Saints?— We wearied our ſelves in the way of wickedneſſe. — What hath pride profited us? — All theſe things are paſſed away like a ſhaddow, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5. Sometimes, in ſtead of perſonating one, divers are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented on the theater, as, Who is this that comes from <hi>Edom,</hi> with his garments from <hi>Bozrah?</hi> that is glorious in his apparell, travelling in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſtrength. I that ſpeak in righteouſneſſe, mighty to ſave. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art thou red in thy apparell, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the wine-fat? I have trodden the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe alone, and of the people there was none with me. For I will tread them in my anger, and trample them in my fury; and their blood ſhall be ſprinkled upon my garments, and I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170374:37"/>will ſtain all my raiment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.1, 2, 3. We have a little ſiſter, and ſhe hath no breaſts; what ſhall we do for our ſiſter in the day when ſhe ſhall be ſpoken for? If ſhe be a wall, we will build upon her a palace of ſilver; and if ſhe be a dore, we will encloſe her with boards of cedar, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Addubitatio, eùm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus quaerere, unde incipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ubi deſinendum, quid po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimùm dicendum omnino fit.</hi> Quint. l. 9. c. 2.</note> Aporia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aporia</hi> is, as it were, a caſting about, and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating with our ſelves in a doubtfull buſineſs, what way to take. The Steward ſaid within himſelf, What ſhall I do? for my Lord taketh away from me my Stewardſhip. I cannot dig, and to beg I am aſhamed. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.3. I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chirſt, which is far better: nevertheleſs, to abide in the fleſh is more needfull for you, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.22, 23, 24. Such deliberations by an <hi>anthropopathy</hi> are aſcribed to God himſelf O <hi>Ephraim</hi> what ſhall I do unto thee? for your goodneſſe is as the morning clowd, and as the dew it goeth away, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.4. So, <hi>Ib.</hi> 11.8. How ſhall I give thee up, <hi>Ephraim?</hi> how ſhall I deliver
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170374:38"/>thee, <hi>Iſrael?</hi> how ſhall I make thee as <hi>Admah?</hi> how ſhall I ſet thee as <hi>Zeboim?</hi> Mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together. What reward ſhall I give unto the Lord for all the benefits he hath done unto me? I will receive the cup of ſalvation, and call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vowes now in the preſence of all his people. Right dear in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.11, 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>A Dubitatione non procul abhorret Communicatio, cum aut ipſos adverſarios conſulimus, aut quando cum judicibus delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Quint. l. 9. c. 2.</note> Anacoinoſis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anacoinoſis</hi> debates the matter with others, and admits of ſcruples; but, ſo far, as we may plauſibly decide them. And here a <hi>Prolepſis,</hi> the foreſeeing and anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of doubts, is moſt naturall. Will a man rob his God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye ſay, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings. Ye are curſed with a curſe; for ye have robbed me, even the whole nation, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8, 9. Thou wilt ſay, The bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches be broken off that I might be graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed in: Well, becauſe of unbelief they vvere broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170374:38"/>faith; be not high-minded, but fear. For if God ſpared not the naturall branches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.19, 20, 21. Thou wilt ſay unto me, Why doth he yet find fault, for who hath reſiſted his vvill? Nay, but, O man, vvho art thou that replieſt againſt God? Shall the thing framed ſay to him that formed it, Why haſt thou made me thus? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>By this Scheme, any controverſies of the Schools may be rhetorically hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as, Thou vvilt tell me, There is a purgatory, by vvhich <hi>David</hi> paſſed through fire and vvater, to a place of refreſhing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. But this muſt be meant of temporall affliction, vvhich <hi>David</hi> in this life had paſſed. But, After this life there is a priſon, vvhence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption may be had upon payment of the uttermoſt farthing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. Alluſions give not Concluſions; and the priſon mentioned is no purging of the ſoul, but urging of a pious and timely agreement, to prevent further incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies. But vvhy vvere men bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed for the dead, if it did the dead no good? Baptiſed they vvere in their ovvn blood, vvhich they ſhed, rather then
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170374:39"/>they vvould bevvray their brethren. But 'tis knovvn, the Fathers held Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. But never as a tenent of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a matter of diſcourſe, vvith a <hi>forſitan verum eſt,</hi> as St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Decked vvith this <hi>Anacoinoſis</hi> is <hi>Rabſhekah's</hi> ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, What confidence is this vvherein thou truſteſt? Thou ſayeſt, I have coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and ſtrength — <hi>Egypt</hi> is but a bruiſed reed, vvhich vvill pierce the hand of him that leans upon it — But if ye ſay, We vvill truſt in the Lord our God; is it not he vvhoſe high places and vvhoſe altars <hi>Hezekiah</hi> hath taken avvay?— 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Conceſſiò, cùm aliquid eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em iniquum videmur cauſae fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duciâ pati.</hi> Quint. l. 9. c. 2. <hi>Gracis dicitur etiam</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guram hanc Confeſſunem vocâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
                     </note> Synchoreſis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Synchoreſis</hi> grants as much, as the adverſarie can in reaſon deſire; yet ſhewes, that it makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for him. Behold, thou art called a Jew, and reſteſt in the Law, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy boaſt of God, and knoweſt his will, and approveſt the things that are more excellent, being inſtructed out of the Law, and art confident that thou thy ſelfe art a guid of the blind, a light of them that are in darkenſſe, an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170374:39"/>of the fooliſh, a teacher of babes, which haſt the forme of knowledg, and the truth in the law. Thou that teacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal? thou that ſayeſt a man ſhould not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultry, doſt thou commit adultry? thou that abhorreſt idols, doſt thou commit ſacriledg? thou that makeſt thy boaſt of the law, through breaking the law diſhonoureſt thou God? <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. The Jews require a ſigne, and the Greeks ſeek after wiſdom, but we preach Chriſt crucified, a ſtumbling block to the Jews, and to the Greeks fooliſhneſſe; but unto them which are called, both Jewes, and Greekes, Chriſt the power of God, and the vviſdome of God. Becauſe the fooliſhneſſe of God is vviſer then men, and the vveakneſſe of God ſtronger then men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. Am I a God at hand, ſaith the Lord, and not a God a far off? can any hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſecret places, that I ſhall not ſee him ſaith the Lord? Do not I fill heaven, and earth, ſaith the Lord? <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.23, 24. Upon vvhich diſſention, the audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are uſually deſired to judg. And novv inhabitants of Jeruſalem, and men of Judah, judg, I pray, between me and my vineyard. What could I have done more
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170374:40"/>to my vineyard than I have done unto it? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.3, 4. I ſpeak to vviſe men, judg you vvhat I ſay; The cup of bleſſing, which vve bleſs, is it not the communion of the blood of Chriſt? The bread, vvhich vve break, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15, 16. Ye Hypocrits, ye can diſern the face of the sky, and of the earth; but hovv is it that ye do not diſcern this time? yea, and vvhy of your ſelves judg ye not vvhat is right? <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.56, 57.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Paſsionem, ſeu affectam af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferens;</hi> ſuch things as move the mind to love, hatred, &amp;c.</note> Of Patheticks.</head>
                  <p>IN this vve have the heighth of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, vvherein <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> appear as <hi>ſons of thunder, Mar.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtabs the hearts of his auditory to a trembling proſtration, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall we do?, Act.</hi> 14.11, 12. <hi>Apollos,</hi> the eloquent Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrian, mightily convinced the Jevves in publick, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. For an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to vvhich, 1. The affections are to be conſidered, that are to be vvrought upon. 2. The vvorking upon
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170374:40"/>them diverſly, by Scripture - Pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
                  <p>Affections to be wrought upon may be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently reduced to
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Love.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Hatred.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Hope.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Fear.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. <hi>Joy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. <hi>Sorrow.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. <hi>Zeal.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Motives to Love.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Love</hi> reſpects God, our ſelvs, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. <hi>David</hi>'s love to God is expreſſ'd in divers places extatically, O how amiable arethy dvvellings, thou Lord of hoſts! My ſoul hath a deſire and longing to enter into the courts of the Lord: my heart and my fleſh rejoyce in the Living God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. Happy Sparrovvs and Svvallovvs vvhich there may have a neſt or houſe; to vvhich, a paſſage through this vale of miſery is a procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from ſtrength to ſtrength; vvhere one dayes entertainment is better, than a thouſand ſpent in vvorldly pleaſure. The tents of ungodlineſſe may be held delectable dvvellings; but I had rather be a dore-keeper in the houſe of my
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170374:41"/>God, than the chief commander in the ſtatelieſt palaces, <hi>Ib.</hi> So every vvhere in all his devotions, ſuch flaſhes of love break out: The Lord is my ſtrength and my ſhield, my heart hath truſted in him, and I am helped. Therefore my heart danceth for joy, and in my ſong vvill I praiſe him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.8. Like as the Hart deſires the vvater-brooks, ſo longeth my ſoul after thee, O God. My ſoul is a thirſt for God, yea, even for the living God; O vvhen ſhall I come to appear before the preſence of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2. I have ſet God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies before me, for he is on my right hand, therefore I ſhall not fall. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my heart vvas glad, and my glory rejoyced, my fleſh alſo ſhall reſt in hope. For thou vvilt not leave my ſoul in hell, neither vvilt thou ſuffer thine holy One to ſee corruption. Thou ſhalt ſhevv me the path of life: in thy preſence is the fulneſſe of joy, and at thy right hand there is pleaſure for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. The men of thy hand, and vvorldlings, may take pleaſure in their portions in this life, vvhoſe bellies thou filleſt vvith thy hid treaſures. They have children at their deſire, and leave the reſt of their ſubſtance for their babes. But as
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170374:41"/>for me, I will behold thy preſence in righteouſneſſe, and when I awake up after thy likeneſſe, I ſhall be ſatisfied, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14, 15, 16. This of <hi>David</hi>'s, <hi>de arte amandi,</hi> is to be ſtudied. The ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall motives thereunto, are. 1. <hi>Gods ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der love</hi> to us. 2. <hi>His ineſtimable benefits</hi> beſtowed, and continued upon us. For what brutiſh diſpoſition will not be taken to love him, from whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth his being, and all that he hath? Is it an ordinary expreſſion of love from the King of Kings to the durty Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, in Egyptian ſlavery? Iſrael is my Son, even my firſt borne, and I ſay unto thee, Let my ſon goe, that he may ſerve me: and if thou refuſe to let him goe, behold I will ſlay thy ſon even thy firſt born, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22, 23. And often he had brought them out, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of mighty <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and all their oppoſites, and ſupplied their wants. What heart would not melt to ponder that affectionate winning ſpeech? And now <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what doth thy Lord thy God require of thee? but to fear thy God, and to walk in his waies, and to love him, and to ſerve thy Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul? <hi>Deuter.</hi> 10. More patheticall
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170374:42"/>is that (if it may be) concerning their hard uſage (though deſerved) from <hi>Aſſur</hi> and <hi>Babel. Iſrael</hi> is a ſcattered ſheep, the lyons have driven him away: firſt the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> hath devoured him, and laſt this <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> hath broken his bones. Therefore, thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, behold I will puniſh the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and his land; as I have puniſhed the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and I will bring <hi>Iſrael</hi> again into his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and he ſhall feed in <hi>Carmel,</hi> and <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and his ſoul ſhall be ſatisfied upon mount <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Gilead.</hi> In thoſe dayes, and at that time, ſaith the Lord, the iniquity of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſought for, and there ſhall be none; and the ſins of <hi>Judah,</hi> and they ſhall not be found: for I will pardon them whom I reſerve. Go up againſt the land of the rebells, over againſt it, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the inhabitants of <hi>Pekoda</hi> that are to be viſited, waſte, and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy after them, ſaith the Lord, and do according to all that I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 50. If this love take not, what ſhould the conſiderations worke, 1. that it is the Lord that woeth us, that made us, and not we our ſelves. 2. that loved ſo the world,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170374:42"/>being his enemies,
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.16. Rom. 5.10. Col. 1.21.</note> that he ſent his only begotten ſon to redeem us from helliſh ſlavery to an everlaſting kingdome. 3. that ſent his holy ſpirit to be our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. to helpe our infirmities. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. and to cry Abba father. 4.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> his word to be a perpetuall lanthorn unto our feet, and a light unto our pathes 5. his bleſſing, for our ſupply in all neceſſaries, &amp; all conveniences: Verily thou ſhalt be fed. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.3. When young lyons do lack, and ſuffer hunger, thoſe that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10.</note> his protection and ſafe conduct from the roaring Lion,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.0</note> and his complices, that walketh about ſeeking whom he may devoure. 7. his deliverance from all contempts,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.41.</note> and preſſures. <hi>Motives to preſerve &amp; love our ſelves.</hi> What can be more patheticall then that of our Saviour? What is a man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole world and loſe his owne ſoul? or what ſhall a man give in exchange for his ſoul? <hi>Matth,</hi> 16.26. or that of <hi>Job,</hi> What is the hope of the hypocrit? though he hath gaine. When God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away his ſoul, will God hear his cry when trouble commeth upon him? Will he delight himſelfe in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty?
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170374:43"/>will he all way call upon God? <hi>Job</hi> 26.8. Or that of the Apoſtle, Know you not that your members are the the members of Chriſt? ſhal I take the members of Chriſt, and make them the members of an harlot? God forbid. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. Know ye not, that ye are the temple of God? and the ſpirit of God dwelleth in you? if any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth the temple of God, him God will deſtroy. For the Temple of God is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whoſe temple ye are, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16, 17. Ye are not your own, ye are bought with a price, therefore glorify God in your body, and your ſpirit, which are Gods. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20. <hi>For the loving of Gods Church, and our neighbours, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> what can be more pathetical then that ſpeech watered with teares of our Saviour over <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> When he was come neer, he beheld the city, wept over it, ſaying, If thou hadſt known, even in this thy day, the things that belong unto thy peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41, 42. The Apoſiopeſis makes it more paſſionate. As that of <hi>Moſes</hi> for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; O this people have ſinned a great ſin, and made them Gods of gold, yet now if thou wilt forgive their ſin! If
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170374:43"/>not, blot me I pray thee out of the book which thou haſt written, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.31, 32. which St. <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth in plainer ſpeech, I ſay the truth in Chriſt, I ly not, my conſcience bearing me witneſſe in the holy ghoſt, that I have great heavyneſſe, and continuall ſorrow in my heart. For I could wiſh my ſelfe were accurſed from Chriſt for my brethren, my kinſmen acording to the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3. And what a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation have we of <hi>Davids</hi> for <hi>Saul</hi> his enemy? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.17. And of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> for <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that had uſed him ſo barbarouſly, in his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Threnes? Which are a ſufficient pattern where love ſhould be opened and placed: which our Saviour urgeth as the cheife mark of his followers. A new commandement I give you, that ye love one another: as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By this ſhall all men knovv, that ye are my diſciples, if ye love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.34, 35. Which is farther urged by that beloved diſciple, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. from the 7 v. to the end of the <hi>Chapter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170374:44"/>
                  <head>Motives to hatred.</head>
                  <p>May be eſpecially bent againſt, 1. <hi>ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſſe.</hi> 2. <hi>impertinences.</hi> 3. <hi>ſordid ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice.</hi> 4. <hi>bestiall luxury.</hi> 5. <hi>brutiſh inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</hi> 6. <hi>perſidious breach of promiſes, oathes, and vowes.</hi> 7. <hi>and rebellion againſt ſuch as God hath ſet over us.</hi> For the firſt; To the <hi>Ant,</hi> thou ſluggard, conſider her wayes, and be wiſe; which having no guid, overſeer, or ruler, provideth her food in the ſummer, and gathereth her food in the harveſt. How long wilt thou ſleep ô ſluggard? when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleep? yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little folding of thy hands to ſleep: So ſhall thy poverty come as one that travelleth, and thy vvant as an armed man, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. Why ſtand ye here Idle? <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. Belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods, vvhoſe glory is their ſhame. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.r9. to whom the Apoſtle would have no victuall afforded. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10. Notwithſtanding. 2. ſuch pragmaticall,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and buſy-bodies will work not at all, as they ſhould, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order all, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.11. theſe will be digging a pit, which themſelves fall into; breaking hedges till a ſerpent
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170374:44"/>bite them; removing ſtones and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wood, whereby they ſhall be hurt and endangered, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.8. and ſlaves on horſ-back, when Princes goe on foot. <hi>ib.</hi> Promiſing liberty to others when they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. Women will have their ſhare amongſt them with their tattling,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and idle running from houſe to houſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.13. And ſome of the pick-thanke tencher-chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, who will take upon them to epiſ copize it in other mens dioceſſes, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 4.13. till a judgment fall upon them which they cannot avoyd. 3 Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our waving the deciſion between two brethren for a matter of pelfe, with this exemplary put-off, Man who made me a judg? or a divider over you? lanceth this ſordid avarice, with the propoſall of a Parable of that baſe rich churle, that was all for the inlarging his barnes, without thinking on Him that ſent the corne; that any ingenious perſon would deteſt the caſe of the wretch, who applauded himſelfe in the gain of his Grain, to the loſſe of his ſoul, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. And who can think upon the drunken ſottiſhneſſe of clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>Nabal</hi> without indignation, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170374:45"/>deteſtation? who could not afford good words, where good deeds were due. Who is <hi>David,</hi> or who is the ſon of <hi>Jeſſe?</hi> There be many ſervants that now a dayes break away every man from his maſter. Shall I then take my bread and my water, and my fleſh, that I have killed for my ſhearers, and give unto men, whom I know not whence they be? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.10, 11. Little knew this caitiffe (that was ſuch a ſon of <hi>Belial,</hi> that a man could not ſpeak to him) what miſcheif was neer him, and his; if his wive's courteous demeanure had not prevented it; but God let it not ſo paſſe, <hi>Ib.</hi> This ſordid humour by the Apoſtle is termed <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> that praeferreth his muck before his Maker, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. the doltiſh vanity of which is touched by the preacher, When goods increaſe, they are increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that eat them, and what good is there to the owners thereof? ſaving the beholding of them with their eyes, and his fooliſh ſon perchance ſhall ſpend all: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.11.14. Who vvould not loath the labour, that brings ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing an in-com? 4. To repreſent how much beſtiall luxury is to be deteſted, the parable of <hi>Dives</hi> vvith the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170374:45"/>may be inſiſted upon 1. backed moſt pathetically by that of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, They ate, they drank, they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried—til the flood came, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all. And as aftervvards in <hi>Lots</hi> dayes in <hi>Sodom,</hi> they ate, they drank, they ſold, they planted, they builded, till fire and brimſtone from heaven marred their market, <hi>Luk,</hi> 17. vvhere <hi>Lots</hi> wife is pillarred for a mark of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. And <hi>Eſau's</hi> bad bargain, in parting vvith his birthright for a morſell of meat, regiſtred for a caution to all poſterity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12, 16. 5. Brutiſh inhumanity may be diſplayed to the deteſtation of the auditors, in the uſage of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> by his bretheren, They ſaid one to another, Behold this dreamer cometh, come novv therefore, and let us ſlay him, and caſt him into ſome pit, and vve vvill ſay, ſome evill beaſt hath devoured him, and vve ſhall ſee vvhat vvill become of his dreames, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.19. Thus they brought his feet to be hurt in the ſtocks, the iron entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſoul. Of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> vvhom they plunged ſo in the mirie dungeon, that he vvas fain to be dravvn up vvith cords, and caſt-clouts, and rotten rags put under, to ſave his fleſh from gaull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170374:46"/>
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 38.12. Of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> whom they ſtoned, at leaſt poſſeſſed with a phrenſy, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.58. Of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was like to be pulled in peices between the factions of the Phariſees, &amp; Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Act.</hi> 23. (6. Breach of oaths and promiſes may be rendred odious by <hi>Zedekiah's</hi> heavy doome, for revolting from <hi>Nebuchadnezer,</hi> to whom he was obliged by oath, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.13. And what a miſery fell upon the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> for wronging the <hi>Gibeonites?</hi> to whom their forefathers had ſo long before obliged themſelves by oath? <hi>Joſ.</hi> 9, though all that <hi>Saul</hi> did was out of his zeal to <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.2.</note> and <hi>Judah.</hi> (7) what can ſet out Rebellion to be hated more in his gaſtly colours, than the ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> with all that belonged to them? <hi>Num.</hi> 16. The prodigious hanging of <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> and <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. And the fearfull end of <hi>Judas,</hi> the traitor, in <hi>Akeldama, Act.</hi> 1.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Motives to Hope</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hope</hi> layeth hold on 1. <hi>deliverances,</hi> 2. <hi>praeſervation.</hi> 3. <hi>conſummation,</hi> from which ariſe all ſpirituall comfors. God
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170374:46"/>is our hope, and ſtrength, a very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent helpe in trouble? therefore will we not feare, Though the earth be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and though the hills be carried in the midſt of the ſea. though the waters thereof rage, and ſwell, and though the mountaines ſhake at the tempeſt of the ſame. The rivers of the flood thereof would glad the city of God—God is in the midſt; therefore ſhall ſhe not be removed. God ſhall help her, and that right early. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then make much adoe, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are moved, but God hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his voice, and the earth ſhall melt away, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. God is called the hope of Iſrael, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 14.8. which maketh not aſhaimed, <hi>Rom,</hi> 8.24. to which ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is attributed. <hi>Rom,</hi> 8.24. whoſe emblem is an anker, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19. which is layd up for us in heaven, whereof we have heard in the word of the truth of the goſpell, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. and therefore with the work of faith, and labour of love the Apoſtle will have the patience of hope in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing, to be remembred, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. Upon this hope of deliverance was grounded the reſolute anſwer of the three children to angry <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170374:47"/>We are not carefull to anſwer the, in this matter; if it be ſo, our God, whom we ſerve, is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us out of thine hand O King. But if not, be it known unto thee, O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the golden image that thou haſt ſet up, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17, 18. This hope was the onely help King <hi>Darius</hi> could find for <hi>Damel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 6.16.</note> Thy God vvhom thou ſerveſt continually, he will deliver thee 2. <hi>for help of preſervation,</hi> vve have a veyn of golden oare running through all the Pſalmes, and allmoſt all the Scripture. I vvill not be afrayd of ten thouſand of people, that have ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt me round about, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.6. The Lord is my light, and ſalvation, whom then ſhall I fear? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of vvhom then ſhal I be afraid? When the vvicked, even mine enimies, and my foes came about me to eate up my fleſh, they ſtumbled and fell, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. Though I vvalk through the valley of the ſhadovv of death, I vvill fear no evill; for thou art vvith me, thy rod and thy ſtaff comfort me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. Confidence againſt taking thought, we
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170374:47"/>have preſſed by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25. Take no thought for your life what ye ſhall eat— <hi>ad finem:</hi> and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence reproved, Why are ye fearfull? <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.26. (3. <hi>For inflaming the hope of conſummation,</hi> what can be more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall then that of our Saviour? Let not your hearts be troubled, ye beleeve in God, beleeve alſo in me. In my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe are many manſions: if it were not ſo, I would have told you, I go to prepare a place for you, <hi>Joh,</hi> 14.1, 2. Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you, not as the world giveth give I unto you: Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid—if ye loved me, ye would rejoyce, <hi>ib.</hi> 27, 28. A glimpe onely, and taſt of this joy, put <hi>Peter</hi> beſide himſelfe, Maſter it is good for us to be here—let us here pitch tabernacles, and not downe to the world againe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Motives to Fear.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> is the betraying of thoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours, which reaſon offereth, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 17, 12. ariſing from dangers, which reaſon telleth us we are unable to withſtand. Theſe dangers may affright
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170374:48"/>us 1. <hi>in our temporall estate.</hi> 2. <hi>in our ſpirituall.</hi> 3. <hi>in our eternall being here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> For temporall afrightments, what thunders are ſo terrible ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as thoſe againſt 1. <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and Egypt for his perfidious and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dealing with Gods people?
<note place="margin">Ezech. 29.</note> 2. againſt Tyrus, and their King for their pride and luxury? 3. againſt Babylon? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. and 14. for their captivating and inſulting upon Gods people. 2. For his temporal eſtate, <hi>Cain</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not;
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.14.</note> but the feare of a guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience was a Fury that ever haunted him, My puniſhment is greater then I can bear. Behold, thou haſt driven me out this day from the face of the earth; and from thy face ſhall I be hid, and I ſhall be a fugitive, and a vagabond, and it ſhall come to paſſe that every one that findeth me ſhall ſlay me. A ſcantling of the third, It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31. This fcarfulneſſe, in propoſing the law, was ſo terrible, that the people could not endure that which was commanded; and if ſo much as a beaſt touch the mountain, it ſhall be ſtoned and thruſt through with a dart: and ſo terrible was the ſight,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170374:48"/>that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, I exceedingly feare, and quake, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.20, 21. What hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour will then be (can any heart ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) when the ſun ſhall become as black as ſack-cloth of hair, and the moone and the ſtars of heaven fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the earth, even as the fig-tree caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her untimely figs, when ſhe is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a mighty wind, when the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhall depart as a ſcroul rolled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and every mountaine and iland ſhall be removed out of their places; when the Kings of the earth, and the great men, and the rich men, and the chief captains, and the mighty men, and every bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and every free-man ſhall hide themſelves in the dens, and in the rocks of the mountaines, and ſhall ſay unto the rocks, and mountaines, Fall on us, and to the hills, Cover us, and hide us from the face of him, that ſitteth upon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb: for the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. When the diſmall doome is once pronounced, Go ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my father into everlaſting fire, prepared for the devill, and his angells, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170374:49"/>
                  <head>Motives to Joy.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joy,</hi> the ayme of all our deſires, muſt be rayſed eſpecially on the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, 1. <hi>of joy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> 2. <hi>comfort in a good conſcience.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and thankfull uſe of temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> Theſe depend one on the other. Temporals delight not, if conſcience be not ſatisfied; &amp; conſcience receives not content, but from aſſurances from the holy Spirit, that all is well. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the fruits of the ſpirit, this joy is ſerved in with love, which quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all the reſt. The fruit of the Spirit is lov, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, goodnes, faith, meeknes, temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, againſt ſuch there is no law. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.22, 23. Upon this is grounded that holy frolick (if the word profane not) of the Apoſtle to the Philippians, Rejoyce in the Lord alwaies, and again I ſay rejoyce. Let your moderation be knowen unto all men, the Lord is neer at hand, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4, 5. Upon which grounds, we have the excitation of the church, O come let us ſing unto the Lord, let us heartily rejoyce in the ſtrength of our ſalvation, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 95. O
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170374:49"/>be joyfull in the Lord all ye lands—<hi>Pſal.</hi> 100. O ſing unto the Lord a new ſong—<hi>Pſal.</hi> 98. And divers other <hi>Pſalms;</hi> ſet to the ſame key of joy. This was the rejoycing of the bleſſed-Virgin My ſpirit hath rejoyced in God my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <hi>Luk:</hi> 1.47. That which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour exhorteth his diſciples unto, In this rejoyce not, that the ſpirits are ſubject to you; but rather rejoyce, that your names are written in heaven 2.
<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20</note> All the dayes of the afflicted are evill: but he that is of a merry heart (upon a good conſcience) hath a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall feaſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.15. This merry heart maketh a cheareful countenance; but by the ſorrow of the heart the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is broken, <hi>Ib.</hi> For our rejoycing is this, the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in the world, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. Thus the Apoſtles, when they were beaten, and threatned after their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, by the high prieſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, departed from the preſence of the Council, rejoycing that they were accounted worthy to ſuffer for his name, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.41. It was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170374:50"/>to have a conſcience voyd of offence towards God, and towards men, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16. And the Hebrews tooke joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods, knowing in themſelves, that they had in heaven a better, and an enduring ſubſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. 3. Joy and thankfullneſſe for temporall bleſſings are not onely approved, but enjoyned, Thou ſhalt rejoyce before the Lord (in acknowledgment of temporal bleſſings) <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.12.18. At the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the firſt fruits, and tithes, after a ſet paryer, it is added, Thou ſhalt rejoyce in every good thing, which the Lord thy God hath given unto thee, and unto thine houſe, thou, and the Levite, and the ſtranger that is among you, <hi>Deut:</hi> 26.11. When God crowneth the yeer with goodneſſe, and the clouds drop fatneſs upon the dwellings of the wilderneſſe, the little hills are brought in to rejoyce on every ſide: when the folds ſhall be full with ſheep, the vallies alſo ſhall ſtand ſo thick with corne, that they ſhall laugh and ſing. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.12. Whereupon the Kingly prophet ſets forth a proclamation, O prayſe the Lord, for it is a good thing to ſing praiſes unto our God; yea a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170374:50"/>joyfull and pleaſant thing it is, to be thankefull, <hi>Pſal</hi> 147.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Motives to Sorrow.</head>
                  <p>A ſorrowfull ſpirit is a ſacrifice to God, deſpiſe not, O Lord, humble and contrite hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.9. <hi>Sorrow</hi> ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth commonly from any thing that croſſeth our deſires, and therefore may be either, 1. <hi>godly;</hi> or 2. <hi>worldy.</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both which, we have that of the Apoſtle, Though I made you ſorry with a letter, I do not repent, though I did repent, for I perceive that the ſame Epiſtle hath made you ſorry, though it be but for a ſeaſon. Now I rejoyce, not that ye were made ſorry, but that ye ſorrowed to repentance, for ye were made ſorry after a godly manner, that ye might receive dammage by us in nothing: for godly ſorrow worketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to ſalvation, not to be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of; but the ſorrow of the world worketh death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.8.9.10. <hi>Motives to Godly ſorrow,</hi> are frequently met with in Scripture; For 1. <hi>private corruptions.</hi> 2. <hi>publick calamities.</hi> 3. <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayling preſſures, and inſultations of Satan, and his adhaerents,</hi> to the ſcandall of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170374:51"/>chriſtian religion, and profeſſon. 1. What an heart-breaking was this to <hi>David?</hi> Behold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my mother conceive, or warme m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. Mine iniquities are gone over my head, and are a ſore burden for me, too heavy for me to beare, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38 4. Innumerable troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are come about me, my ſins have taken ſuch hold upon me, that I am not able to looke up; yea, they are more in number, then the hairs of my head and my heart hath failed me. O Lord, let it be thy pleaſure to deliver me, make haſte O Lord to help me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.15, 16. When thou with rebukes doſt chaſten man for ſin, thou makeſt his beauty to conſume avvay, as it vvere a moth fretting of a garment: Every man therefore is but vanity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.12. whence St. <hi>Paul.</hi> bemoans himſelfe, I delight in the law of God after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man:
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> but I ſee another law in my members, warring againſt the law of my mind, bringing me into captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the law of ſin, which is in my members. O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death? ſin muſt needs bring ſadneſſe to many, that proved ſo odious
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170374:51"/>to God's nature, that it ruined the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, bereaved <hi>Adam</hi> of Gods favour and Paradiſe, could not be expiated but by the ſon of God, who knew no ſin, yet was made ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſnes of God in him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. (2. How publick calamities affect the heart with ſorrow of all thoſe that are true of heart, may be gathered by thoſe paſſionate paſſages of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Look away from me, for I will weep bitterly, labour not to comfortmè, becauſe of the ſpoyling of the daughter of my people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.4. Of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> My bowells, my bowels I am pained to the very heart. The vvall of my heart makes a noyſe vvithin we, I cannot hold my peace, becauſe thou haſt heard O my ſoule, the ſound of the trumpet, the alarm of war. Deſtruction upon deſtruction is cryed, for the vvhole land is ſpoyled. Suddainly are my tents ſpoyled, and my curtaines in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Hovv long ſhall I ſee the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and hear the ſound of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet? For my people is fooliſh, they have not knowen me, they are ſottiſh children, they have not underſtanding they are wiſe to do evill, but to do good they have no knowledg, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170374:52"/>O that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of teares, that I might weep day and night for the ſlain of the daughter of my people. Oh that I had in the Wilderneſſe a lodging place of wayfaring men, that I might leave my people, and go from them: for they be all adulterers, an aſſembly of treacherous men, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.1. Thus <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is bemoaned, made drunk with the cup of fury, that had none of her ſons to take her by the hand to guide her, of all thoſe ſhe hath brought up, but lay as a bull in a net at the head of all the ſtreets, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. (3. Complaints of Sataincall inſultations are, The ungodly for his own luſt doth perſecute the poore: He is ſo proud that he careth not for God, neither is God in all his thoughts: His wayes are always grievous, thy judgments are far above out of his ſight, and therefore defieth he all his enemies. For he hath ſaid in his heart, Tuſh I ſhall never be caſt down, there ſhall no harm happen unto me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. This complaint is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. To which, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction is given, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. and 49. <hi>Jeremy</hi> harps upon the ſame ſtring, Wherefore doth the way of the wicked
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170374:52"/>proſper? wherefore are they happy, that deal very treacherouſly? Thou haſt planted them, yea they have taken root; they grow, yea they bring forth fruit. Thou art neer in their mouthes, but far from their reines. But it followes, Thoſe that have ſo trodden downe the Lords portion, and deſolated the land, ſhall reap Thornes inſtead of Wheat, put themſelves to pain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profit. For they ſhall be aſham'd of their revenues, becauſe of the fierce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Motives to Zeal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zeal;</hi> which may be good or bad. Good is either, 1 for <hi>Gods honour,</hi> 2 <hi>houſe,</hi> or 3 <hi>people.</hi> The firſt was of <hi>Elias,</hi> I have been very jealous for the Lord God of hoſts, becauſe the children have forſaken thy Covenant, thrown down thy altars, and ſlain thy people with the ſword; and I, even I onely, am left, and they ſeek my life to take it away, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.14. For this zeal <hi>Phineas</hi> is commended of God. <hi>Phineas</hi> the ſon of <hi>Eliezar,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Aaron</hi> the prieſt, hath turned my wrath away from the children of Iſrael, while he was zealous for my
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170374:53"/>ſake amongſt them, that I conſumed not the children of Iſrael in my jealouſy <hi>Num.</hi> 25.11. Of this zeal <hi>Jehu</hi> boaſted, Come with me, and ſee my zeal for the Lord: ſo they made him ride in his chariot, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.16. The 2d ſort of zeale may be typified in David, The zeale of thy houſe hath eaten me up, and the reproaches of them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached thee are fallen upon me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.9. My zeale hath conſumed me, becauſe mine enemies have forgotten thy words, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.139. But pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſed by our Saviour, when he found in the temple, thoſe that ſold oxen, and ſheep, and doves, and the changers of money ſitting, He made a ſcourge of ſmall cords, and drove them out of the Temple, and the ſheep, and the oxen, and poured out the changers-mony, and over-threw the tables, and ſaid unto them that ſold doves, Take theſe things hence, and make not my Fathers houſe, an houſe of merchandize. And the diſciples remembred that it was written, The zeale of thine houſe hath caten me up, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.14. Much different from the zeale, of our modern zealots <hi>the zeale of whom eateth up God's houſe.</hi> 3. For zeale to Gods people; The zeale
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170374:53"/>of Moſes and St. <hi>Paul</hi> are notoriouſly eminent, which was ſeconded by that of that reſolute Prieſt <hi>Mattathias,</hi> who when he ſaw a Jew ſacrificing to idols, was inflamed with zeale, and his reins trembled, neither could he forbeare to ſhew his anger according to judgment: wherefore he ran and ſlew him upon the altar. Alſo the Kings commiſſioners, who compelled men to ſacrifice, he killed at that time, and the altar he pulled downe. Thus dealt he zealouſly for the law of God, as <hi>Phineas</hi> did to <hi>Zambri</hi> the ſon of <hi>Salom.</hi> 1 Maccab. 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bad zeale</hi> ſpendeth it ſelfe either in.
<note place="margin">Nemeſis. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Zelotypia.</note> 1 <hi>revenge.</hi> 2 <hi>rejoycing at others ruines,</hi> or 3 <hi>in impetuous undertakings, and purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, not acording to knowledg.</hi> Belonging to the firſt kind was that of Saul, for rooting out the Gibeonites, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.2. And thoſe more then forty, that had bound themſelves under a curſe, that they would neither eate, nor drinke till they had ſlaine Paul, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.12 <hi>Haman</hi> was ſicke of this diſeaſe, and therefore he thought it ſcorne to lay hands on <hi>Mordecai</hi> alone, but all the Jewes muſt be deſtroyed with him. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 3.6. All his riches, multitude of children, advancement above the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170374:54"/>Peers of the Kingdom affected him lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, in compariſon in his vaunting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his freinds, and <hi>Zerith</hi> his wife; yea <hi>Heſter</hi> (ſaith he) the Queen lett no man come in with the King, to the banquet ſhe had prepared, but my ſelfe; and to morrow am I invited un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her alſo, with the King: yet all this availeth me nothing, ſo long as I ſee <hi>Mordecai</hi> the Jew ſitting at the Kings gate, <hi>Heſt.</hi> 5.13. (2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Joy in anothers ruines,</hi> is a zeal which leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Chriſtians. It was a beſeeming thought in furious <hi>Jehu,</hi> that after the tumbling of painted <hi>Jezabel</hi> down from a window, and trampling her under his horſes feet, from the midſt of his cups he could command, Go ſee now this curſed woman, and bury her, for ſhe is a King's daughter, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.34. For want of which, <hi>Edom</hi> is ſharply taxed, For thy violence againſt thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for ever in the day, that thou ſtooddeſt on the other ſide, in the day that the ſtranger car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away his forces captive, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiners entred into his gates, even the waſt one of them. <hi>Obad.</hi> 10. Such was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he rejoycing of the dwellers on the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170374:54"/>earth over the two Witneſſes ſlain, whom they would not ſuffer to be put in graves, but were merry over them, and ſent gifts one to another, becauſe they tormented them that dwelt on the earth. 3. <hi>Blind zeal,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 11.9.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth on any thing, putting no differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt good or bad, friends or foes. This carrieth moſt commonly with it a miſtake, in all the reſt of the paſſions; as in the 1 of dotage or luſt, for love. 2 Spite to the perſon or revenge, for hatred to the fault. In the 3 prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, deſpair, or groundles cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity is obtruded for hope. In the 4 cowardice and needleſs trembling, for fear. In the 5 ridculous merriments, for true joy. In the 6 cauſeleſs dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and melancholly-dumps, for groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſadneſs. Of all which, examples from Scripture may be gathered.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170374:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Characters, Deſcriptions, or Idea's.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I.
<note place="margin">See that thou make all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the pattern, ſhewed to thee in the Mount. Exod. 25.40. Act. 7.44. Heb. 8.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Characters,</hi> as they come to hand, and for the eaſier remembring of them, (where the text will bear it) may be caſt into heptades, As <hi>God will protect, them that call upon him, from</hi> 1 <hi>Wicked men, ungodly that feare not God.</hi> 2 <hi>evill that are injurious to men.</hi> 3 <hi>fooliſh in their practiſes.</hi> 4 <hi>vaine in their projects.</hi> 5 <hi>lying in their diſcourſes.</hi> 6 <hi>blood-thirſty in their perſecutions.</hi> 7 <hi>deceitfull in all their contracts, and dealings, Pſal.</hi> 5.4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>The way of Cain</hi> (<hi>Jude.</hi> v. 11.) conſiſted of 7 crooked-miſleading ſteps. 1 <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy,</hi> he would ſacrifice as well, and readily as <hi>Abel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.12.</note> 2 <hi>His aemulating hatred</hi> to his brother, by reaſon of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred devotion. 3 This brought him to murder him. 4 which he endeavoureth to ſlubber over with a ſurly lye,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.9.</note> I know not where my brother is: am I his keeper? 5 his deſperation upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, without the leaſt remorſe, but
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170374:55"/>rather grumbles at God's juſt ſentence; My puniſhment is greater than I can beare. Thou haſt fined me too deep, dealt too hardly with me. 6 his oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rather to withſtand his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then ſubmiſſion to mitigate it; and marries, gets children, builds a citty, and names it <hi>Enoch</hi> to eternize his ſon's name.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> 7 the profaneſs of himſelfe and his, who wholly forſook God, and prided themſelves in their inventions, which is intimated by their contrary courſe, taken by the <hi>Setheans,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed themſelves to call on God, whom the <hi>Cainites</hi> had forſaken.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Theſe ſix things doth the Lord hate: and ſeven are an abhomination,</hi> 1. A proud look, 2. A lying tongue, 3. Hands that ſhead innocent blood, 4. An heart that deviſeth wicked imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; 5. Feet that be ſwift in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to miſchiefe, 6. A falſe witneſs that ſpeaketh lyes, 7. And him that ſoweth diſcord among brethren, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="4">IV.
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Marked men for revived offences in our time,</hi> 1. <hi>Cain</hi> for fratricide, 2.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Cham,</hi> for inſulting irreverently on his father's nakedneſſe, 3. <hi>Iſhmael</hi> for
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170374:56"/>flouting <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and playing, (it ſhould ſeem) on his name,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> given by God, terming him ſome ſuch thing as a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous young Maſter, which is called a kind of perſecution, 4. <hi>Korah,</hi> for rebellious contradiction,
<note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> 5. <hi>Saul</hi> for uſurping the Prieſts office in ſacrificing, ſparing <hi>Amalek</hi> againſt God's expreſſe command,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.</note> butchering innocent <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> and all the inhabitants of <hi>Nob,</hi> the city of the Prieſts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> 6. <hi>Ahaz</hi> for Sacriledge, and continued Idolatry when Gods hand was upon him, with this Character ſet upon him, This that King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> 7. <hi>Zedekiah</hi> for perjury, and neglecting Gods Prophets,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.</note> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Sin's genealogy,</hi> 1. Suggeſtion, <hi>from Satan,</hi> 2. Delectation, <hi>was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,</hi> 3. Conſent, <hi>ſhe took it,</hi> 4. Act, <hi>did eate,</hi> 5. Contagion, <hi>gave her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> 6. Horrour of Conſcience, <hi>ſaw their nakedneſſe, feared, hid themſelves,</hi> 7. Cenſure of puniſhment, <hi>becauſe thou hast done this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>Practiſes of the Jewes againſt their owne, in the fury of their ignorant zeal,</hi> 1. They killed the Lord Jeſus, 2. And their owne Prophets, 3. Perſecuted
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170374:56"/>the Apoſtles, 4. Pleaſe not God, 5. Are contrary to all men, 6. Forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Gentiles, [deceived] that they might be ſaved, 7. Fill up the meaſure of their ſins, [to the brim,] that the wrath of God may come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them at the utmoſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15, 16.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>A repreſentation of the Divine Majesty,</hi> I ſaw the Lord ſitting upon a 1. Throne, high and lifted up, (which is applyed to Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.) above it ſtood the 2. Seraphims, each one had 3. ſix wings; with twain He covered his face, and with twaine he did fly, and 4. cryed one to another, and ſaid, 5. Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of hoſts, the whole earth is full of his glory: and the poſts of the door moved at him that cried, and the houſe was filled with ſmoak, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. <hi>A larger repreſentation to Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi> in 1 four living creatures, each having the likeneſſe of a man with 4 faces, Of a man, a Lion, an Ox, an Eagle, 2. fourwings to ſhew their ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 3. Sparkling calves feet, like burniſhing braſſe, 4. Hands of a man under their wings on their four ſides,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170374:57"/>5. Four wheels animated one with in another full of eyes, 6. A throne of Saphire arched with a Rain-bow, 7. Upon the likeneſſe of the Throne, was the likeneſſe of the appearance of a man upon it.</p>
               <p n="9">IX.
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Saviour is ſet forth by his</hi> 1. Attire, a garment down to the foot, girt about the Paps with a Golden gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> intimating his prieſt-hood, 2. The colour of his Head and haire, white like Wool, as white as Snow; ſhewing his eternity, 3. The flaming of his eyes, expreſſing his omniſciency, 4. His feet like fine braſſe in a furnace, leading to his revenge againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 5. Seven ſtars in his right hand, aſſuring the protection of his Church againſt all oppoſers,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 6. A ſharp two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edged ſword from his mouth, to cut down all impediments,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> 7. His coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance as the Sun ſhining in his ſtrength, with a voyce of the ſound of many waters, to the daunting and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of all thoſe that have neglected him.</p>
               <p n="10">X. <hi>A good Biſhop</hi> ſhould have, 1. Good education, as <hi>Moſes</hi> learned in all the wiſdome of the Egyptians, <hi>Act.</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170374:57"/>7.22. The children of the Prophets under <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Eliſha.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel, Act.</hi> 22.3. Which ſociety our Saviour graced, in ſitting in the midſt of the Doctours,
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.36.</note> hearing them, and asking them queſtions. 2. He is advanced to his chair not am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly ſought after, Be not ye called, Rabbi, Maſters,
<note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> but humble your ſelves that ye may be exalted, 3. He muſt be free from buſying himſelfe in impertinencies, and intangling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with many worldly buſineſſes,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.15.</note> 4. He is to Ordain and ſettle Prieſts in every Pariſh, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. and neither ſuddenly,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.1.3.</note> or without due examination to lay his hands on any, 5. He is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to convince Innovators, and wrangling Sophiſters,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> and to chaſe away Wolves, and Foxes from the Flock of Chriſt, 6. Againſt an Elder he is not to receive an accuſation, but under two or three witneſſes: But thoſe that ſin (ſcandalouſly) rebuke them before all, that others may alſo fear, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> Honouring them with double honour, that labour in the Word and Doctrine. 7. He is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly to withdraw himſelfe from
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170374:58"/>proud, and peremptory Fellowes, knowing nothing, but doting about queſtions, and ſtrife of words, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cometh ſtrife, railings, and evill ſurmiſes, perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds and deſtitute of truth, ſuppoſing that gain is godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. <hi>A virtuous woman</hi> is of price far above Rubies, becauſe, 1. The heart of her Hous-band may ſafely truſt in her, ſo that he ſhall have no need of ſpoil. 2. She will do him good, and not evill all the dayes of her life, 3. She ſeeketh Wooll, and Flax, and worketh willingly with her Hands, 4. She is like the Merchant's ſhip, that bringeth food from afar, 5. She riſeth when it is yet night, and giveth meat to her houſehold, and a portion to her Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, 6. She conſidereth a Field, and buyeth it; with the fruit of her hands, <hi>ſhe planteth a vineyard,</hi> 7. She girdeth her loines with ſtrength, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her armes, 8. She perceiveth her Merchandiſe is good, Her candle goeth not out by night. 9. She layeth her Hands to the Spindle, and her Hands hold the Diſtaffe, 10. She
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170374:58"/>ſtretcheth out her armes to the poor, yea ſhe reacheth her hands to the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, 11. She is not afraid of the ſnow, for her houſehold; for all her houſehold are clothed with ſcarlet. 12. She ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her ſelfe covering of tapeſtry; her clothing is ſilke, and purple. 13. Her Housband is known in the gate, when he ſitteth among the Elders of the land. 14. She maketh fine linnen, and ſelleth it, and delivereth girdles to the merchant. 15. Strength and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our are her cloathing, and ſhe ſhall rejoyce in time to come. 16. She open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her mouth with wiſdome, and in her tongue is the law of kindneſs. 17. She looketh well to the wayes of her houſhold, and eateth not the bread of idleneſſe. 18. Her children riſe up and call her bleſſed, her housband alſo, and he praiſeth her. 19. Many daughters have done virtuouſly, but thou excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them all. 20. Favour is deceitfull, and beauty is vain: but a woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be prayſed. 21. Give her of the fruits of her hands, and let her owne workes prayſe her in the gates. <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. <hi>The picture of old age</hi> Eccleſ. 12.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170374:59"/>to which the ſun, the light, the moon and ſtars yield little comfort, by reaſon of one weaknes tumbling upon another as clouds returning after raine, one ſtorme ſeconding another. 2. For in it, 1. <hi>the keepers of the houſe ſhal tremble,</hi> that is, the arms and hands (the readieſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the body) weakned by pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and other infirmities. 2, <hi>the ſtrong men bow themſelves,</hi> thighs, and legs through Sciatica, aches, defluxions. 3. <hi>the grinders ceaſe, becauſe they are few,</hi> the teeth, moſt loſt; they left, rotten. 4. <hi>and thoſe that look out by the windows be darknes,</hi> which muſt be meant of the eyes. 5. <hi>and the doores ſhall be ſhut in the ſtreets,</hi> the lips or chaps little imployed <hi>when the ſound of the grinding is low,</hi> when the teeth have little to do. 6. <hi>and he ſhall riſe up at the voyce of the bird,</hi> awake early in the morning at cock-crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or bird's ſinging, in regard old men through infirmity ſleep little. 7. <hi>And the daughters of muſick ſhall be brought low,</hi> the wind-pipes to utter, or ears to hear or delight in ſongs, as old <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zillai</hi> acknowledged 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.35. <hi>Alſo they ſhall be aſraid of that which is high, and fear ſhal be in the way,</hi> old men dread
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170374:59"/>to climbe, and hazzard themſelves in dangerous wayes by reaſon of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity of their limbs. Now though theſe are ſufficient remembrancers, yet nearer ſymptoms come with new me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento's. 1. the hoarineſs or baldneſſe of the head, <hi>as white as the bloſſoms of an almond tree.</hi> 2. the belly or legs loaden with dropſies or gouts puffing him up and making him lazy, and <hi>miſhapen as a locuſt;</hi> where <hi>graſhopper</hi> denotes a graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper's unweildy devouring to no purpoſe. 3. the thought of his <hi>long home</hi> approaching, and ſight of <hi>mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> diſhearten him from all worldly pleaſure, and cloud him with ſadneſſe. 4. eſpecially when he, ſtooping in the back, ſhewes that <hi>the ſilver chord</hi> of <hi>ſpina medulla</hi> is looſed, which was wont to truſſe him up more upright 5. <hi>the golden bowle,</hi> the <hi>pia mater</hi> which conteins the brain, is crack'd. 6. <hi>the pitcher,</hi> the miſeraïc, cava and porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veines are ſtopped, or broken, that they bring not, as formerly, good blood from the fountaine of the liver to chear up the whole body. 7. And laſt, when <hi>the wheel</hi> of the lungs, which compaſſe and preſerve the <hi>ciſtern</hi> of the heart,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170374:60"/>from whence the vitall ſpirits are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed by the arteries, through the whole body to hold (as we ſay) life and ſoul together, then that muſt of force be thought upon, that <hi>Dust ſhall return to the earth as it was, and the ſpirit ſhall return to God that gave it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">XIII <hi>Neceſſaries for a Preacher,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.9.</note> 1. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduity in teaching others, <hi>Becauſe the preacher was wiſe, he ſtill taught the people knowledg.</hi> 2. choice of matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment well ſtudied, <hi>He gave good heed, and ſought out, and ſet in order many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> 4, Rhetoricall expreſſions, <hi>The preacherſought out to find acceptable words.</hi> 5. warrantable doctrine, by its owne grounds, and confirmation of the maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the aſſembly, <hi>that which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten was upright, even words of truth. The words of the wiſe are as goads, and nails faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the maſters of the aſſemblies.</hi> 6. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Word, which is given by the hand of one ſhepheard, Chriſt our Saviour. 7. Abſtaining from diſtracting ſtudies, which wearie the fleſh in making many books, when his owne bible would give content if it be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, that we need (eſpecially for matters of ſalvation) no other Direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170374:60"/>
               <p n="14">XIIII <hi>The arms of a Chriſtian Souldier againſt</hi> 1. principalities. 2. powers. 3. rulers of the darknes of this world. 4. ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places. 1. <hi>the girdle of truth</hi> for the loyns. 2. for the breaſt, <hi>the breſt-plate of righteouſneſs.</hi> 3. for the feet, <hi>the preparation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of peace.</hi> 4. for the left hand next the heart, <hi>the ſhield of faith to quench the fiery darts of the Divel,</hi> 5. for the right hand <hi>the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God.</hi> 6. for the head, <hi>the helmet of ſalvation.</hi> 7. for the accompliſhing of all, <hi>prayer and ſupplications in the Spirit, with watching and all perſeverance.</hi> Eph. 6.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170374:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. Of <hi>Antitheſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. IT is written that <hi>Abraham</hi> had two ſons, the one by a bondmaid, the other by a free-woman: but he that was of the bond-woman was born after the fleſh; but he of the free woman was by promiſe. Which things are an Allegory. For theſe are the two covenants, the one from mount Sinai, which gendereth to bondage, which is <hi>Hagar;</hi> for this <hi>Hagar</hi> is mount Sinai in Arabia, and anſwereth to Jeruſalem that now is, and is in bondage with her children, but Jeruſalem which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove is free, and is the mother of us all, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. Where may be noted correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, and antitheſes between 1. <hi>Hagar</hi> a bond-woman, and <hi>Sarah</hi> free. 2.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſmael, Hagar's</hi> ſon after the fleſh; and <hi>Iſaac, Sarah's,</hi> according to promiſe. 3. Sinai in Arabia the deſert, and Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in the land of promiſe. 4. Sinai called by the Arabians <hi>Hagar,</hi> allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Law; Jeruſalem, the mother of us all, the covenant of the goſpell thence proclaimed. 5. dependers of the Law for juſtification, Hagarens born to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170374:61"/>bondage; adherents to faith, the ſons of Sarah, born to freedom. 6. fleſhly Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelites, perſecutors; ſpirituall ſons of <hi>Sarah,</hi> for a time under the croſſe. 7. the cenſure, upon the perſecuting juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiaries, Caſt out the bond-woman and her ſon: on the other ſide, The free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman's children ſhall be heyrs.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Antitheſis, between Christ and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Rom.</hi> 5. (1) Not as the offence, ſo is the free gift: that, by juſtice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; this by grace abounded, 2. That included the venome of one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or propagated but one offence originall: this quits from originall, and infinite actualls, 3. That, by one brought in the tyranny of death; this by one the gift of Righteouſneſſe and reign in Life, 4. That the root of juſt Condemnation, this of the free gift of Juſtification, 5. That made all men ſinners, this made many righteous, 6. The horridneſs of that is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by the Law, the abounding of grace is more illuſtrious by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. 7. That was attended by reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſin unto Death, this by Grace to Righteouſneſſe and Eternall Life.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Antitheſis, between the fleſh, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170374:62"/>the Spirit, Rom.</hi> 7. where, 1. The fleſh brings forth fruit unto death, the Spirit contendeth to ſerve in newneſſe of Life, 2. The fleſh holds by the old letter, the ſpirit by a new tenure, 3. The fleſh worketh death by that which is good, that ſin might become excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſinfull: the Spirit clears it ſelfe by pleading a pardon, 4. By the fleſh we are ſold unto ſin, by the Spirit we attaine redemption, 5. In the fleſh, to will may be preſent with us, but deeds follow not; but the ſpirit urgeth to performe, 6. The inward man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in the Law of God: but the Law of the members carry the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents againſt the Law of the Mind, 7. The fleſh makes up the body of ſin, the Spirit obtaineth deliverance by Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Antitheſis between the Body before, and after, the Reſurrection,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1. It is ſowen in Corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption, 2. It is ſowen in Honour, it is raiſed in Glory, 3. It it ſowen in weakneſſe, it is raiſed againe in power, 4. It is ſowen a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body, 5. It is ſowen, as the firſt <hi>Adams</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170374:62"/>iſſue, having onely a living ſoul; it is raiſed, as the ſecond <hi>Adams</hi> purchaſe, made a quickning ſpirit, 6. The firſt is of the Earth earthly, the ſecond from the Lord of Heaven heavenly, 7. The firſt carrying the image or ſtamp of earth, from which he was taken; the ſecond the badg of Heaven, to which he is advanced.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Antitheſis between true pastors, and impoſtors or ſcorners,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. We are made a ſpectacle to the World, and to Angells, and to Men. 1. We are fools for Chriſts ſake, but ye are wiſe in Chriſt, 2. We are weak, but ye are ſtrong, 3. Ye are honoured, but we are deſpiſed, as it appeareth, becauſe at this preſent hour, we both hunger and thirſt, and are naked, and are buffetted, and have no certain dwelling place, and labour, working with our owne hands, 4. Being revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led we bleſſe, 5. Being perſecuted we ſuffer it, 6. Being defamed we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate, 7. We are made the filth of the world, and are the off-ſcouring of all things unto this day.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>Gods Miniſters to be approved,</hi> 1. In much patience, 2. In afflictions,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170374:63"/>3. In neceſſities, 4. In diſtreſſes, 5. In ſtripes, 6. In impriſonment, 7. In tumults, 8. In labours, 9. In watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, 10. In faſtings. By, 1. Pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 2. By knowledge, 3. By long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, 4. By kindneſſe, 5. By the Holy Ghoſt, 6. By love unfained, 7. By the word of truth, 8. By the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, 9. By the armour of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, 10. On the right hand and on the left, 11. By honour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, 12. By evill report and good report. As, 1. Deceivers and yet true, 2. As unknown and yet well known, 3. As dying, yet behold we live, 4. As chaſtned and not killed, 5. As ſorrowfull, yet alwayes rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, 6. As poor and yet making ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rich, 7. As having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>The chast Matrone, and the whore of Babylon, are thus differenced,</hi> 1. The Matron is cloathed with the Sun from Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. The great whore with Scarlet, and Gold, and Pearls from the earth, 2. The Matron hath the Moon, and ſpotted-changes under her Feet; the Whore ſitteth on many waters, which will at length fail her,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170374:63"/>3. The Matron hath a Crown of 12 Stars upon her Head; the Whore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares with a frontlet of blaſphemies, Myſtery, <hi>Babylon</hi> the great,
<note place="margin">Rev. 17.5.12.2.</note> Mother of harlots, and abhominations of the earth, 4. The Matron is fruitfull, and travelling to bring forth Children; the Whore is drunk with the blood of Saints and Martyrs, and is more for deſtruction then honeſt propagation, 5. The Dragon watcheth the Matron to devour her off-ſpring; but mounts the Whore upon a beaſt, which hath ſeven Heads and ten Horns, the moſt terrible and majeſticall in all his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh mewes, 6. The Dragon with his Angells enter the liſts in the Whore's quarrell; but <hi>Michael</hi> and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents undertake for the Matron, to the Dragon's ſhamefull routing, 7. The Matron is furniſhed with Eagle's wings to be nouriſhed, and preſerved in the wilderneſſe; but the whore is deſerted and hated by her Partizans, who ſhall make her deſolate, and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.36.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170374:64"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Parables, and Similitudes.</head>
                  <p>I Have ſpoken by the Prophets, and I have multiplyed viſions and uſed ſimilitudes by the hand of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Parallel betwixt Chriſt, and Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k.</hi> 1. both had like Ordination. 2. by oath, not by deſcent. 3. without prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, or ſuceſſors, father, mother, beginning or end of life. 4. greater than <hi>Abraham,</hi> by reaſon of receiving tithes from him, and <hi>Levi</hi> in his loins. 5. King of righteouſneſſe and peace. 6. bleſſing as the greater, but not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from him 7. both offering for others, not for their own ſins, as Chriſt the antitype did once for all, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Between a miniſter,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.15.</note> and a candle.</hi> Men light not a candle, and put it under a buſhel, but on a candleſtick and it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth light to all that are in the houſe, 1. A candle lightens not it ſelfe, but muſt be lightned of, and from, another: ſo a Miniſter muſt have his calling and gifts from God's illumination, How
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170374:64"/>ſhall he preach except he be ſent? 2.
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> A candle is not lighted to be hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a buſhel, neither a Miniſter or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to behave himſelfe as a dumb Dog, ſleeping through idleneſſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatisfied through covetouſneſſe, and drowning himſelfe and others in all kind of ſurquedry, 3.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 56, 10.</note> A candle muſt be ſet on a candleſtick, for its more commodious giving light: So muſt the Miniſter reſide in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned Cure, wherein he may do moſt good: he muſt not biſchop it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans diceceſſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. nor boaſt without his meaſure in other mens lines, 4.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.15.</note> A candle giveth light to all indifferently that are in the houſe: So a Miniſter ſhould apply himſelfe to all within his compaſſe, making himſelfe all things to all men, that by all means he may ſave ſome,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.22.</note> 6. A candle ſometimes wanteth ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers; ſo may a Miniſter, correptions: But it ſhould be with ſnuffers of Gold belonging to the Sanctuary, and by ſuch as know, and have right to uſe them; not by polluted fingers or other meanes, which may rather extinguiſh, then make them burn the brighter; 7. A candle inverted is extinguiſhed by
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170374:65"/>his owne nutriment: and ſo a Miniſter who turning that light downeward, which ſhould turne upward, moſt commonly is fryed to deſtruction in his owne fatneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The courſe of mans life reſembleth an expedition at ſea,</hi> wherein 1. our nativity is the ſhore we lanch from. 2. the church the bottom wherein we are carried. 3. the world the ſea. 4. Chriſt the pilot. 5. the Scripture, the compaſſe 6. the gifts of the holy ghoſt, the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous gales we ſaile by. 7. <hi>Sinus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahae,</hi> the haven of happineſſe we are bound for. Then are they glad becauſe they be at reſt; and ſo he bringeth them to the haven where they would be, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 30.</p>
                  <p>God's people, as lively ſtones, are built up a ſpirituall houſe, an holy prieſthood to offer up ſpirituall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>A good man in divers reſpects reſembleth a ſtone.</hi> 1. A ſtone is to be hammered fit for the place, before it be laid in building: So a faithfull man by education and ſuffering, is faſhioned to the calling, wherein he is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. 2. A ſtone is meaſured before it be laid in its place: So the faithfull
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170374:65"/>ſhould be placed according to their abilities. 3. a ſtone muſt be hard to endure wind and weather, beſide caſuall aſſaults: the like oppoſition muſt be expected of thoſe that live godly, 4. a ſtone in a lower range bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ſuperiour, covers his inferiour, and juſtles not with his fellowes ſet beſide: the like reſpect ſhould be had amongſt good men to ſuperiours, to peers, and inferiors. 5. a ſtone butting out muſt be beaten back to range with his fellowes: and ſo muſt too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward exorbitants, which ambitiouſly perk before their brethren. 6. a moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſtone muſt be plucked out to have a ſounder ſet in his place: ſo in defect of a treacherous <hi>Judas,</hi> a <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> is juſtly choſen. 7. ſtones that are not well cemented continue not a building: ſo without the cement of charity, chriſtianity ſhattereth, which is built upon the foundation of the Prophets, and Apoſtles; Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe being the chiefe corner-ſtone, in whom all the building fitly framed together groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord: In whom yee alſo are builded together for an habitation of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170374:66"/>God through the Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am a ſtranger with thee, and a ſojourner as all my fathers were, Pſal.</hi> 39.12. (1) A pilgrim profeſſeth himſelf to be ſo by carriage, and habite: ſo ſhould a chriſtian. 2. he paſſeth-by obvious ſights, as not belonging unto him: this becometh a mortified chriſtian. 3. He builds not in every Inne he lodgeth in: ſo ought a chriſtian. 4. He burdens not himſelfe with unneceſſary carriage: ſuch would be comberſome to a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. 5. He ſhrinks not at impediments &amp; dangers which croſſe him, but conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtruggles through them: much more ſhould a chriſtian. 6. He maketh the beſt of the entertainment he meets with any where, not calling fire from heaven upon inhoſpitable Samaritans, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.54: this ſorts with the calme ſpirit of a Chriſtian. 7. He allwayes hath a deſire to his true home: this ſhould be the ayme and comfort of a chriſtian. <hi>For while we are in the body we are abſent from the Lord: for we walk by faith, and not by ſight: and therefore ſhould be confident and willing rather to be abſent from the body, and to be preſent with the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170374:66"/>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>For the Lords day</hi> there is ground in nature: Some time is to be ſet apart, for the publick worſhip of God, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in all religions. And the ſame ground there is <hi>for Epiſcopacy,</hi> that ſome perſons ſhould be ſet a part, and prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before others to performe, and overſee the performance of that ſacred worſhip. 2. A patterne for that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jewes, one day deſigned in ſeven. The like was alſo for church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goverment, by chiefe Prieſts, Prieſts, and Levites: to which are anſwerable our Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the goſpell, The moſt that is ſaid for appointing the Lords-day for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip is the intimation, not prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of our Saviour, but practice of the Apoſtles: and ſo much we have, and more, in the differencing of the xij A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, lxx diſciples, and the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles and Church upon it. 4. The mention of the Lords day <hi>Apocal.</hi> 1. is not ſo cleare an evidence for the ſtabliſhing Sunday, for the jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ſabbath; as the Epiſtles to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells of the 7 Churches there menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, conclude, that thoſe were the Biſhops of thoſe Churches, whom our
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170374:67"/>Saviour alloweth by writing unto. 5. There cannot be brought any thing concluding for the Lords day out of the New teſtament ſo fully, as that for ſubordinat degrees in eccleſiaſtical hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy. God hath ſet ſom in the church firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. ſuch as were <hi>Timothy and Titus, Paul and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> who ordained Presbyters, and preſcribed rules unto them. 6. The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Lords day for Chriſtian aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies in place of the Jewiſh ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and deductions; will hardly be made ſo conſpicuous, as the deduction of epiſcopacy, from the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in all eminent churches, before the late interruption of our licentious times: as it appears in the genuine and undoubted epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and all antiquity. 7. And thoſe that are almoſt ſuperſtitious for the Sabbath, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg a kind of epiſcopacy; which they would be content to bear (if they might have the managing of it) and be obedient to the orders, and controul of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>St. Peter and St. Paul parallel'd.</hi> 1. Both called immediately by Chriſt;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170374:67"/>the one, before; the other, after his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion. 2. Both principall Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> of the Jewes, <hi>Paul</hi> of the Gentils. 3. Both full of humility; <hi>Peter</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Paul</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.9. 1 Pet. 2.13, 14. Rom. 13.</note> Both earneſt for the ſupream autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of magiſtrates. 5. Neither <hi>Peter</hi> for the claime of the Pope, his pretended ſucceſſor; nor <hi>Paul</hi> in his large epiſtle to the Romans, ſo much as give a hint of Papall ſupremacy. 6. Both are ſent by, and give account to the Church. <hi>Peter</hi> to them of Jeruſalem, <hi>Paul</hi> to the Antiochians. 7. Both take it well to be reproved: <hi>Peter</hi> reproved by <hi>Paul</hi> to his face. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>Peter</hi> for his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3: 16:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170374:68"/>
                  <head>Of Similies.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Similies</hi> are uſed by all, for illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and though they prove not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, yet they teach more eaſily then firmer grounds; eſpecially, thoſe that be fed with Milk, rather than ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Meat, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12, 13. It was the method of teaching by the beſt Maſter; Whereunto ſhall I liken the men of this generation, and to what are they like? They are like unto children ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Market-place, and ſaying, We have piped unto you, but ye have not danced; we have mourned to you, and ye have not wept. For <hi>John</hi> came neither eating bread, nor drinking wine, and ye ſay, He hath a Devill: the Son of man is come eating and drinking, and ye ſay, Behold a glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonous man, and a wine-bibber, a friend of Publicans and ſinners: but wiſdome is juſtified of all her children, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. Are ye not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſo way-ward, and childiſh as the Town-boyes? brawling for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, or nothing, in the Market place? that nothing can pleaſe you, neither
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170374:68"/>
                     <hi>Johns</hi> ſtrictneſſe nor my eaſie hand, but both muſt be rejected, and ſlandered by you?</p>
                  <p>As <hi>Balaams</hi> curſed intention was turned into a bleſſing, <hi>Eſau's</hi> fury into a friendly meeting with his brother <hi>Jacob, Sauls</hi> warrant to perſecute into a grand commiſſion for promoting the Goſpell: ſo God may charme the hearts of the <hi>Labans</hi> of theſe times (Take heed thou ſpeak not to <hi>Jacob</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or bad, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.) to be ſo far from injuring him any way, as to give him not ſo much as an ill word. This is the generation of them that ſeek him, even that ſeek thy face, O <hi>Jacob, Pſ.</hi> 24.6.</p>
                  <p>The man that walkes, 1. Not in the counſell of the ungodly] will have nothing to do with their plots, who take not God with them, 2. Stands not in the way of ſinners] concurring with, and juſtifying their actions, 3. Sits not in the ſeat of the ſcornefull] contemning and jeering at thoſe that take better courſes, 4. But delights in the Law of the Lord] more then in the attaining of polfe and praefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 5. And in that law is exerciſed
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170374:69"/>day and night] whereas other ſpend their time in revelling, and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. Shall be like] not a hollow Reed pearing out of the Mire, but, 1. a Tree ſpreading abroad his boughs, 2. planted by a provident hand, that expects good of it, 3. not in a barren ſoyle, or rocky mountain, expoſed to all bluſtring wind and weather; but, 4. by the water's ſide, which will mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter it gratious moiſture, that it may not ſtand for a ſhew onely, or ſhade, but, 5. bring forth fruit, 6. and that not unnaturally, or unſeaſonably to be blaſted, but in due ſeaſon, when ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, 7. The leaſe of ſuch a Tree ſhall not wither with Winter, nor be ſcorched in Summer; but ſhall flouriſh, ſpreading abroad like a Cedar in Lebanon, and bringing forth fruit moſt in their age.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
